The Author’s Apology

Mrs. Warren’s Profession has been performed at last, after a delay of only eight years; and I have once more shared with Ibsen the triumphant amusement of startling all but the strongest-headed of the London theatre critics clean out of the practice of their profession. No author who has ever known the exultation of sending the Press into an hysterical tumult of protest, of moral panic, of involuntary and frantic confession of sin, of a horror of conscience in which the power of distinguishing between the work of art on the stage and the real life of the spectator is confused and overwhelmed, will ever care for the stereotyped compliments which every successful farce or melodrama elicits from the newspapers. Give me that critic who rushed from my play to declare furiously that Sir George Crofts ought to be kicked. What a triumph for the actor, thus to reduce a jaded London journalist to the condition of the simple sailor in the Wapping gallery, who shouts execrations at Iago and warnings to Othello not to believe him! But dearer still than such simplicity is that sense of the sudden earthquake shock to the foundations of morality which sends a pallid crowd of critics into the street shrieking that the pillars of society are cracking and the ruin of the State is at hand. Even the Ibsen champions of ten years ago remonstrate with me just as the veterans of those brave days remonstrated with them. Mr. Grein, the hardy iconoclast who first launched my plays on the stage alongside Ghosts and The Wild Duck, exclaimed that I have shattered his ideals. Actually his ideals! What would Dr. Relling say? And Mr. William Archer himself disowns me because I “cannot touch pitch without wallowing in it.” Truly my play must be more needed than I knew; and yet I thought I knew how little the others know.

Do not suppose, however, that the consternation of the Press reflects any consternation among the general public. Anybody can upset the theatre critics, in a turn of the wrist, by substituting for the romantic commonplaces of the stage the moral commonplaces of the pulpit, platform, or the library. Play Mrs. Warren’s Profession to an audience of clerical members of the Christian Social Union and of women well experienced in Rescue, Temperance, and Girls’ Club work,[1] and no moral panic will arise; every man and woman present will know that as long as poverty makes virtue hideous and the spare pocket-money of rich bachelordom makes vice dazzling, their daily hand-to-hand fight against prostitution with prayer and persuasion, shelters and scanty alms, will be a losing one. There was a time when they were able to urge that though “the white lead factory where Anne Jane was poisoned” may be a far more terrible place than Mrs. Warren’s house, yet hell is still more dreadful. Nowadays they no longer believe in hell; and the girls among whom they are working know that they do not believe in it, and would laugh at them if they did. So well have the rescuers learnt that Mrs. Warren’s defence of herself and indictment of society is the thing that most needs saying, that those who know me personally reproach me, not for writing this play, but for wasting my energies on “pleasant plays” for the amusement of frivolous people, when I can build up such excellent stage sermons on their own work. Mrs. Warren’s Profession is the one play of mine which I could submit to a censorship without doubt of the result; only, it must not be the censorship of the minor theatre critic, nor of an innocent court official like the Lord Chamberlain’s Examiner, much less of people who consciously profit by Mrs. Warren’s profession, or who personally make use of it, or who hold the widely whispered view that it is an indispensable safety-valve for the protection of domestic virtue, or, above all, who are smitten with a sentimental affection for our fallen sister, and would “take her up tenderly, lift her with care, fashioned so slenderly, young, and so fair.” Nor am I prepared to accept the verdict of the medical gentlemen who would compulsorily sanitate and register Mrs. Warren, whilst leaving Mrs. Warren’s patrons, especially her military patrons, free to destroy her health and anybody else’s without fear of reprisals. But I should be quite content to have my play judged by, say, a joint committee of the Central Vigilance Society and the Salvation Army. And the sterner moralists the members of the committee were, the better.

Some of the journalists I have shocked reason so unripely that they will gather nothing from this but a confused notion that I am accusing the National Vigilance Association and the Salvation Army of complicity in my own scandalous immorality. It will seem to them that people who would stand this play would stand anything. They are quite mistaken. Such an audience as I have described would be revolted by many of our fashionable plays. They would leave the theatre convinced that the Plymouth Brother who still regards the playhouse as one of the gates of hell is perhaps the safest adviser on the subject of which he knows so little. If I do not draw the same conclusion, it is not because I am one of those who claim that art is exempt from moral obligations, and deny that the writing or performance of a play is a moral act, to be treated on exactly the same footing as theft or murder if it produces equally mischievous consequences. I am convinced that fine art is the subtlest, the most seductive, the most effective instrument of moral propaganda in the world, excepting only the example of personal conduct; and I waive even this exception in favor of the art of the stage, because it works by exhibiting examples of personal conduct made intelligible and moving to crowds of unobservant, unreflecting people to whom real life means nothing. I have pointed out again and again that the influence of the theatre in England is growing so great that whilst private conduct, religion, law, science, politics, and morals are becoming more and more theatrical, the theatre itself remains impervious to common sense, religion, science, politics, and morals. That is why I fight the theatre, not with pamphlets and sermons and treatises, but with plays; and so effective do I find the dramatic method that I have no doubt I shall at last persuade even London to take its conscience and its brains with it when it goes to the theatre, instead of leaving them at home with its prayerbook as it does at present. Consequently, I am the last man in the world to deny that if the net effect of performing Mrs. Warren’s Profession were an increase in the number of persons entering that profession, its performance should be dealt with accordingly.

Now let us consider how such recruiting can be encouraged by the theatre. Nothing is easier. Let the King’s Reader of Plays, backed by the Press, make an unwritten but perfectly well understood regulation that members of Mrs. Warren’s profession shall be tolerated on the stage only when they are beautiful, exquisitely dressed, and sumptuously lodged and fed; also that they shall, at the end of the play, die of consumption to the sympathetic tears of the whole audience, or step into the next room to commit suicide, or at least be turned out by their protectors and passed on to be “redeemed” by old and faithful lovers who have adored them in spite of their levities. Naturally, the poorer girls in the gallery will believe in the beauty, in the exquisite dresses, and the luxurious living, and will see that there is no real necessity for the consumption, the suicide, or the ejectment: mere pious forms, all of them, to save the Censor’s face. Even if these purely official catastrophes carried any conviction, the majority of English girls remain so poor, so dependent, so well aware that the drudgeries of such honest work as is within their reach are likely enough to lead them eventually to lung disease, premature death, and domestic desertion or brutality, that they would still see reason to prefer the primrose path to the strait path of virtue, since both, vice at worst and virtue at best, lead to the same end in poverty and overwork. It is true that the Board School mistress will tell you that only girls of a certain kind will reason in this way. But alas! that certain kind turns out on inquiry to be simply the pretty, dainty kind: that is, the only kind that gets the chance of acting on such reasoning. Read the first report of the Commission on the Housing of the Working Classes (Bluebook C 4402, 8d., 1889); read the Report on Home Industries (sacred word, Home!) issued by the Women’s Industrial Council (Home Industries of Women in London, 1897, 1s., 12 Buckingham Street, WC); and ask yourself whether, if the lot in life therein described were your lot in life, you would not prefer the lot of Cleopatra, of Theodora, of the Lady of the Camellias, of Mrs. Tanqueray, of Zaza, of Iris. If you can go deep enough into things to be able to say no, how many ignorant half-starved girls will believe you are speaking sincerely? To them the lot of Iris is heavenly in comparison with their own. Yet our King, like his predecessors, says to the dramatist, “Thus, and thus only, shall you present Mrs. Warren’s profession on the stage, or you shall starve. Witness Shaw, who told the untempting truth about it, and whom We, by the Grace of God, accordingly disallow and suppress, and do what in Us lies to silence.” Fortunately, Shaw cannot be silenced. “The harlot’s cry from street to street” is louder than the voices of all the kings. I am not dependent on the theatre, and cannot be starved into making my play a standing advertisement of the attractive side of Mrs. Warren’s business.

Here I must guard myself against a misunderstanding. It is not the fault of their authors that the long string of wanton’s tragedies, from Antony and Cleopatra to Iris, are snares to poor girls, and are objected to on that account by many earnest men and women who consider Mrs. Warren’s Profession an excellent sermon. Mr. Pinero is in no way bound to suppress the fact that his Iris is a person to be envied by millions of better women. If he made his play false to life by inventing fictitious disadvantages for her, he would be acting as unscrupulously as any tract writer. If society chooses to provide for its Irises better than for its working women, it must not expect honest playwrights to manufacture spurious evidence to save its credit. The mischief lies in the deliberate suppression of the other side of the case: the refusal to allow Mrs. Warren to expose the drudgery and repulsiveness of plying for hire among coarse, tedious drunkards; the determination not to let the Parisian girl in Brieux’s Les Avariés come on the stage and drive into people’s minds what her diseases mean for her and for themselves. All that, says the King’s Reader in effect, is horrifying, loathsome. Precisely: what does he expect it to be? would he have us represent it as beautiful and gratifying? The answer to this question, I fear, must be a blunt Yes; for it seems impossible to root out of an Englishman’s mind the notion that vice is delightful, and that abstention from it is privation. At all events, as long as the tempting side of it is kept towards the public, and softened by plenty of sentiment and sympathy, it is welcomed by our Censor, whereas the slightest attempt to place it in the light of the policeman’s lantern or the Salvation Army shelter is checkmated at once as not merely disgusting, but, if you please, unnecessary.

Everybody will, I hope, admit that this state of things is intolerable; that the subject of Mrs. Warren’s profession must be either taboo altogether, or else exhibited with the warning side as freely displayed as the tempting side. But many persons will vote for a complete taboo, and an impartial sweep from the boards of Mrs. Warren and Gretchen and the rest; in short, for banishing the sexual instincts from the stage altogether. Those who think this impossible can hardly have considered the number and importance of the subjects which are actually banished from the stage. Many plays, among them Lear, Hamlet, Macbeth, Coriolanus, Julius Caesar, have no sex complications: the thread of their action can be followed by children who could not understand a single scene of Mrs. Warren’s Profession or Iris. None of our plays rouse the sympathy of the audience by an exhibition of the pains of maternity, as Chinese plays constantly do. Each nation has its own particular set of taboos in addition to the common human stock; and though each of these taboos limits the scope of the dramatist, it does not make drama impossible. If the Examiner were to refuse to license plays with female characters in them, he would only be doing to the stage what our tribal customs already do to the pulpit and the bar. I have myself written a rather entertaining play with only one woman in it, and she is quite heartwhole; and I could just as easily write a play without a woman in it at all. I will even go so far as to promise Mr. Redford my support if he will introduce this limitation for part of the year, say during Lent, so as to make a close season for that dullest of stock dramatic subjects, adultery, and force our managers and authors to find out what all great dramatists find out spontaneously: to wit, that people who sacrifice every other consideration to love are as hopelessly unheroic on the stage as lunatics or dipsomaniacs. Hector is the world’s hero; not Paris nor Antony.

But though I do not question the possibility of a drama in which love should be as effectively ignored as cholera is at present, there is not the slightest chance of that way out of the difficulty being taken by Mr. Redford. If he attempted it there would be a revolt in which he would be swept away in spite of my singlehanded efforts to defend him. A complete taboo is politically impossible. A complete toleration is equally impossible to Mr. Redford, because his occupation would be gone if there were no taboo to enforce. He is therefore compelled to maintain the present compromise of a partial taboo, applied, to the best of his judgement, with a careful respect to persons and to public opinion. And a very sensible English solution of the difficulty, too, most readers will say. I should not dispute it if dramatic poets really were what English public opinion generally assumes them to be during their lifetime: that is, a licentiously irregular group to be kept in order in a rough and ready way by a magistrate who will stand no nonsense from them. But I cannot admit that the class represented by Eschylus, Sophocles, Aristophanes, Euripides, Shakespeare, Goethe, Ibsen, and Tolstoy, not to mention our own contemporary playwrights, is as much in place in Mr. Redford’s office as a pickpocket is in Bow Street. Further, it is not true that the Censorship, though it certainly suppresses Ibsen and Tolstoy, and would suppress Shakespeare but for the absurd rule that a play once licensed is always licensed (so that Wycherly is permitted and Shelley prohibited), also suppresses unscrupulous playwrights. I challenge Mr. Redford to mention any extremity of sexual misconduct which any manager in his senses would risk presenting on the London stage that has not been presented under his license and that of his predecessor. The compromise, in fact, works out in practice in favor of loose plays as against earnest ones.

To carry conviction on this point, I will take the extreme course of narrating the plots of two plays witnessed within the last ten years by myself at London West End theatres, one licensed by the late Queen Victoria’s Reader of Plays, the other by the present Reader to the King. Both plots conform to the strictest rules of the period when La Dame aux Camellias was still a forbidden play, and when The Second Mrs. Tanqueray would have been tolerated only on condition that she carefully explained to the audience that when she met Captain Ardale she sinned “but in intention.”

Play number one. A prince is compelled by his parents to marry the daughter of a neighboring king, but loves another maiden. The scene represents a hall in the king’s palace at night. The wedding has taken place that day; and the closed door of the nuptial chamber is in view of the audience. Inside, the princess awaits her bridegroom. A duenna is in attendance. The bridegroom enters. His sole desire is to escape from a marriage which is hateful to him. An idea strikes him. He will assault the duenna, and get ignominiously expelled from the palace by his indignant father-in-law. To his horror, when he proceeds to carry out this stratagem, the duenna, far from raising an alarm, is flattered, delighted, and compliant. The assaulter becomes the assaulted. He flings her angrily to the ground, where she remains placidly. He flies. The father enters; dismisses the duenna; and listens at the keyhole of his daughter’s nuptial chamber, uttering various pleasantries, and declaring, with a shiver, that a sound of kissing, which he supposes to proceed from within, makes him feel young again.

In deprecation of the scandalized astonishment with which such a story as this will be read, I can only say that it was not presented on the stage until its propriety had been certified by the chief officer of the Queen of England’s household.

Story number two. A German officer finds himself in an inn with a French lady who has wounded his national vanity. He resolves to humble her by committing a rape upon her. He announces his purpose. She remonstrates, implores, flies to the doors and finds them locked, calls for help and finds none at hand, runs screaming from side to side, and, after a harrowing scene, is overpowered and faints. Nothing further being possible on the stage without actual felony, the officer then relents and leaves her. When she recovers, she believes that he has carried out his threat; and during the rest of the play she is represented as vainly vowing vengeance upon him, whilst she is really falling in love with him under the influence of his imaginary crime against her. Finally she consents to marry him; and the curtain falls on their happiness.

This story was certified by the present King’s Reader, acting for the Lord Chamberlain, as void in its general tendency of “anything immoral or otherwise improper for the stage.” But let nobody conclude therefore that Mr. Redford is a monster, whose policy it is to deprave the theatre. As a matter of fact, both the above stories are strictly in order from the official point of view. The incidents of sex which they contain, though carried in both to the extreme point at which another step would be dealt with, not by the King’s Reader, but by the police, do not involve adultery, nor any allusion to Mrs. Warren’s profession, nor to the fact that the children of any polyandrous group will, when they grow up, inevitably be confronted, as those of Mrs. Warren’s group are in my play, with the insoluble problem of their own possible consanguinity. In short, by depending wholly on the coarse humors and the physical fascination of sex, they comply with all the formulable requirements of the Censorship, whereas plays in which these humors and fascinations are discarded, and the social problems created by sex seriously faced and dealt with, inevitably ignore the official formula and are suppressed. If the old rule against the exhibition of illicit sex relations on stage were revived, and the subject absolutely barred, the only result would be that Antony and Cleopatra, Othello (because of the Bianca episode), Troilus and Cressida, Henry IV, Measure for Measure, Timon of Athens, La Dame aux Camellias, The Profligate, The Second Mrs. Tanqueray, The Notorious Mrs. Ebbsmith, The Gay Lord Quex, Mrs. Dane’s Defence, and Iris would be swept from the stage, and placed under the same ban as Tolstoy’s Dominion of Darkness and Mrs. Warren’s Profession, whilst such plays as the two described above would have a monopoly of the theatre as far as sexual interest is concerned.

What is more, the repulsiveness of the worst of the certified plays would protect the Censorship against effective exposure and criticism. Not long ago an American Review of high standing asked me for an article on the Censorship of the English stage. I replied that such an article would involve passages too disagreeable for publication in a magazine for general family reading. The editor persisted nevertheless; but not until he had declared his readiness to face this, and had pledged himself to insert the article unaltered (the particularity of the pledge extending even to a specification of the exact number of words in the article) did I consent to the proposal. What was the result?

The editor, confronted with the two stories given above, threw his pledge to the winds, and, instead of returning the article, printed it with the illustrative examples omitted, and nothing left but the argument from political principles against the Censorship. In doing this he fired my broadside after withdrawing the cannon balls; for neither the Censor nor any other Englishman, except perhaps Mr. Leslie Stephen and a few other veterans of the dwindling old guard of Benthamism, cares a dump about political principle. The ordinary Briton thinks that if every other Briton is not kept under some form of tutelage, the more childish the better, he will abuse his freedom viciously. As far as its principle is concerned, the Censorship is the most popular institution in England; and the playwright who criticizes it is slighted as a blackguard agitating for impunity. Consequently nothing can really shake the confidence of the public in the Lord Chamberlain’s department except a remorseless and unbowdlerized narration of the licentious fictions which slip through its net, and are hallmarked by it with the approval of the Throne. But since these narrations cannot be made public without great difficulty, owing to the obligation an editor is under not to deal unexpectedly with matters that are not virginibus puerisque, the chances are heavily in favor of the Censor escaping all remonstrance. With the exception of such comments as I was able to make in my own critical articles in The World and The Saturday Review when the pieces I have described were first produced, and a few ignorant protests by churchmen against much better plays which they confessed they had not seen nor read, nothing has been said in the press that could seriously disturb the easygoing notion that the stage would be much worse than it admittedly is but for the vigilance of the King’s Reader. The truth is, that no manager would dare produce on his own responsibility the pieces he can now get royal certificates for at two guineas per piece.

I hasten to add that I believe these evils to be inherent in the nature of all censorship, and not merely a consequence of the form the institution takes in London. No doubt there is a staggering absurdity in appointing an ordinary clerk to see that the leaders of European literature do not corrupt the morals of the nation, and to restrain Sir Henry Irving, as a rogue and a vagabond, from presuming to impersonate Samson or David on the stage, though any other sort of artist may daub these scriptural figures on a signboard or carve them on a tombstone without hindrance. If the General Medical Council, the Royal College of Physicians, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Incorporated Law Society, and Convocation were abolished, and their functions handed over to Mr. Redford, the Concert of Europe would presumably declare England mad, and treat her accordingly. Yet, though neither medicine nor painting nor law nor the Church moulds the character of the nation as potently as the theatre does, nothing can come on the stage unless its dimensions admit of its passing through Mr. Redford’s mind! Pray do not think that I question Mr. Redford’s honesty. I am quite sure that he sincerely thinks me a blackguard, and my play a grossly improper one, because, like Tolstoy’s Dominion of Darkness, it produces, as they are both meant to produce, a very strong and very painful impression of evil. I do not doubt for a moment that the rapine play which I have described, and which he licensed, was quite incapable in manuscript of producing any particular effect on his mind at all, and that when he was once satisfied that the ill-conducted hero was a German and not an English officer, he passed the play without studying its moral tendencies. Even if he had undertaken that study, there is no more reason to suppose that he is a competent moralist than there is to suppose that I am a competent mathematician. But truly it does not matter whether he is a moralist or not. Let nobody dream for a moment that what is wrong with the Censorship is the shortcoming of the gentleman who happens at any moment to be acting as Censor. Replace him tomorrow by an Academy of Letters and an Academy of Dramatic Poetry, and the new and enlarged filter will still exclude original and epoch-making work, whilst passing conventional, old-fashioned, and vulgar work without question. The conclave which compiles the index of the Roman Catholic Church is the most august, ancient, learned, famous, and authoritative censorship in Europe. Is it more enlightened, more liberal, more tolerant than the comparatively infinitesimal office of the Lord Chamberlain? On the contrary, it has reduced itself to a degree of absurdity which makes a Catholic university a contradiction in terms. All censorships exist to prevent anyone from challenging current conceptions and existing institutions. All progress is initiated by challenging current concepts, and executed by supplanting existing institutions. Consequently the first condition of progress is the removal of censorships. There is the whole case against censorships in a nutshell.

It will be asked whether theatrical managers are to be allowed to produce what they like, without regard to the public interest. But that is not the alternative. The managers of our London music-halls are not subject to any censorship. They produce their entertainments on their own responsibility, and have no two-guinea certificates to plead if their houses are conducted viciously. They know that if they lose their character, the County Council will simply refuse to renew their license at the end of the year; and nothing in the history of popular art is more amazing than the improvement in music-halls that this simple arrangement has produced within a few years. Place the theatres on the same footing, and we shall promptly have a similar revolution: a whole class of frankly blackguardly plays, in which unscrupulous low comedians attract crowds to gaze at bevies of girls who have nothing to exhibit but their prettiness, will vanish like the obscene songs which were supposed to enliven the squalid dullness, incredible to the younger generation, of the music-halls fifteen years ago. On the other hand, plays which treat sex questions as problems for thought instead of as aphrodisiacs will be freely performed. Gentlemen of Mr. Redford’s way of thinking will have plenty of opportunity of protesting against them in Council; but the result will be that Mr. Redford will find his natural level; Ibsen and Tolstoy theirs; so no harm will be done.

This question of the Censorship reminds me that I have to apologize to those who went to the recent performance of Mrs. Warren’s Profession expecting to find it what I have just called an aphrodisiac. That was not my fault; it was Mr. Redford’s. After the specimens I have given of the tolerance of his department, it was natural enough for thoughtless people to infer that a play which overstepped his indulgence must be a very exciting play indeed. Accordingly, I find one critic so explicit as to the nature of his disappointment as to say candidly that “such airy talk as there is upon the matter is utterly unworthy of acceptance as being a representation of what people with blood in them think or do on such occasions.” Thus am I crushed between the upper millstone of Mr. Redford, who thinks me a libertine, and the nether popular critic, who thinks me a prude. Critics of all grades and ages, middle-aged fathers of families no less than ardent young enthusiasts, are equally indignant with me. They revile me as lacking in passion, in feeling, in manhood. Some of them even sum the matter up by denying me any dramatic power: a melancholy betrayal of what dramatic power has come to mean on our stage under the Censorship! Can I be expected to refrain from laughing at the spectacle of a number of respectable gentlemen lamenting because a playwright lures them to the theatre by a promise to excite their senses in a very special and sensational manner, and then, having successfully trapped them in exceptional numbers, proceeds to ignore their senses and ruthlessly improve their minds? But I protest again that the lure was not mine. The play had been in print for four years; and I have spared no pains to make known that my plays are built to induce, not voluptuous reverie but intellectual interest, not romantic rhapsody but humane concern. Accordingly, I do not find those critics who are gifted with intellectual appetite and political conscience complaining of want of dramatic power. Rather do they protest, not altogether unjustly, against a few relapses into staginess and caricature which betray the young playwright and the old playgoer in this early work of mine.

As to the voluptuaries, I can assure them that the playwright, whether he be myself or another, will always disappoint them. The drama can do little to delight the senses: all the apparent instances to the contrary are instances of the personal fascination of the performers. The drama of pure feeling is no longer in the hands of the playwright: it has been conquered by the musician, after whose enchantments all the verbal arts seem cold and tame. Romeo and Juliet with the loveliest Juliet is dry, tedious, and rhetorical in comparison with Wagner’s Tristan, even though Isolde be both fourteen stone and forty, as she often is in Germany. Indeed, it needed no Wagner to convince the public of this. The voluptuous sentimentality of Gounod’s Faust and Bizet’s Carmen has captured the common playgoer; and there is, flatly, no future now for any drama without music except the drama of thought. The attempt to produce a genus of opera without music (and this absurdity is what our fashionable theatres have been driving at for a long time without knowing it) is far less hopeful than my own determination to accept problem as the normal material of the drama.

That this determination will throw me into a long conflict with our theatre critics, and with the few playgoers who go to the theatre as often as the critics, I well know; but I am too well equipped for the strife to be deterred by it, or to bear malice towards the losing side. In trying to produce the sensuous effects of opera, the fashionable drama has become so flaccid in its sentimentality, and the intellect of its frequenters so atrophied by disuse, that the reintroduction of problem, with its remorseless logic and iron framework of fact, inevitably produces at first an overwhelming impression of coldness and inhuman rationalism. But this will soon pass away. When the intellectual muscle and moral nerve of the critics has been developed in the struggle with modern problem plays, the pettish luxuriousness of the clever ones, and the sulky sense of disadvantaged weakness in the sentimental ones, will clear away; and it will be seen that only in the problem play is there any real drama, because drama is no mere setting up of the camera to nature: it is the presentation in parable of the conflict between Man’s will and his environment: in a word, of problem. The vapidness of such drama as the pseudo-operatic plays contain lies in the fact that in them animal passion, sentimentally diluted, is shown in conflict, not with real circumstances, but with a set of conventions and assumptions half of which do not exist off the stage, whilst the other half can either be evaded by a pretence of compliance or defied with complete impunity by any reasonably strong-minded person. Nobody can feel that such conventions are really compulsory; and consequently nobody can believe in the stage pathos that accepts them as an inexorable fate, or in the genuineness of the people who indulge in such pathos. Sitting at such plays, we do not believe: we make-believe. And the habit of make-believe becomes at last so rooted that criticism of the theatre insensibly ceases to be criticism at all, and becomes more and more a chronicle of the fashionable enterprises of the only realities left on the stage: that is, the performers in their own persons. In this phase the playwright who attempts to revive genuine drama produces the disagreeable impression of the pedant who attempts to start a serious discussion at a fashionable at-home. Later on, when he has driven the tea services out and made the people who had come to use the theatre as a drawing-room understand that it is they and not the dramatist who are the intruders, he has to face the accusation that his plays ignore human feeling, an illusion produced by that very resistance of fact and law to human feeling which creates drama. It is the deus ex machina who, by suspending that resistance, makes the fall of the curtain an immediate necessity, since drama ends exactly where resistance ends. Yet the introduction of this resistance produces so strong an impression of heartlessness nowadays that a distinguished critic has summed up the impression made on him by Mrs. Warren’s Profession, by declaring that “the difference between the spirit of Tolstoy and the spirit of Mr. Shaw is the difference between the spirit of Christ and the spirit of Euclid.” But the epigram would be as good if Tolstoy’s name were put in place of mine and D’Annunzio’s in place of Tolstoy. At the same time I accept the enormous compliment to my reasoning powers with sincere complacency; and I promise my flatterer that when he is sufficiently accustomed to and therefore undazzled by problem on the stage to be able to attend to the familiar factor of humanity in it as well as to the unfamiliar one of a real environment, he will both see and feel that Mrs. Warren’s Profession is no mere theorem, but a play of instincts and temperaments in conflict with each other and with a flinty social problem that never yields an inch to mere sentiment.

I go further than this. I declare that the real secret of the cynicism and inhumanity of which shallower critics accuse me is the unexpectedness with which my characters behave like human beings, instead of conforming to the romantic logic of the stage. The axioms and postulates of that dreary mimanthropometry are so well known that it is almost impossible for its slaves to write tolerable last acts to their plays, so conventionally do their conclusions follow from their premises. Because I have thrown this logic ruthlessly overboard, I am accused of ignoring, not stage logic, but, of all things, human feeling. People with completely theatrified imaginations tell me that no girl would treat her mother as Vivie Warren does, meaning that no stage heroine would in a popular sentimental play. They say this just as they might say that no two straight lines would enclose a space. They do not see how completely inverted their vision has become even when I throw its preposterousness in their faces, as I repeatedly do in this very play. Praed, the sentimental artist (fool that I was not to make him a theatre critic instead of an architect!) burlesques them by expecting all through the piece that the feelings of others will be logically deducible from their family relationships and from his “conventionally unconventional” social code. The sarcasm is lost on the critics: they, saturated with the same logic, only think him the sole sensible person on the stage. Thus it comes about that the more completely the dramatist is emancipated from the illusion that men and women are primarily reasonable beings, and the more powerfully he insists on the ruthless indifference of their great dramatic antagonist, the external world, to their whims and emotions, the surer he is to be denounced as blind to the very distinction on which his whole work is built. Far from ignoring idiosyncrasy, will, passion, impulse, whim, as factors in human action, I have placed them so nakedly on the stage that the elderly citizen, accustomed to see them clothed with the veil of manufactured logic about duty, and to disguise even his own impulses from himself in this way, finds the picture as unnatural as Carlyle’s suggested painting of parliament sitting without its clothes.

I now come to those critics who, intellectually baffled by the problem in Mrs. Warren’s Profession, have made a virtue of running away from it. I will illustrate their method by quotation from Dickens, taken from the fifth chapter of Our Mutual Friend:

“Hem!” began Wegg. “This, Mr. Boffin and Lady, is the first chapter of the first wollume of the Decline and Fall off—” here he looked hard at the book, and stopped.

“What’s the matter, Wegg?”

“Why, it comes into my mind, do you know, sir,” said Wegg with an air of insinuating frankness (having first again looked hard at the book), “that you made a little mistake this morning, which I had meant to set you right in; only something put it out of my head. I think you said Rooshan Empire, sir?”

“It is Rooshan; ain’t it, Wegg?”

“No, sir. Roman. Roman.”

“What’s the difference, Wegg?”

“The difference, sir?” Mr. Wegg was faltering and in danger of breaking down, when a bright thought flashed upon him. “The difference, sir? There you place me in a difficulty, Mr. Boffin. Suffice it to observe, that the difference is best postponed to some other occasion when Mrs. Boffin does not honor us with her company. In Mrs. Boffin’s presence, sir, we had better drop it.”

Mr. Wegg thus came out of his disadvantage with quite a chivalrous air, and not only that, but by dint of repeating with a manly delicacy, “In Mrs. Boffin’s presence, sir, we had better drop it!” turned the disadvantage on Boffin, who felt that he had committed himself in a very painful manner.

I am willing to let Mr. Wegg drop it on these terms, provided I am allowed to mention here that Mrs. Warren’s Profession is a play for women; that it was written for women; that it has been performed and produced mainly through the determination of women that it should be performed and produced; that the enthusiasm of women made its first performance excitingly successful; and that not one of these women had any inducement to support it except their belief in the timeliness and the power of the lesson the play teaches. Those who were “surprised to see ladies present” were men; and when they proceeded to explain that the journals they represented could not possibly demoralize the public by describing such a play, their editors cruelly devoted the space saved by their delicacy to an elaborate and respectful account of the progress of a young lord’s attempt to break the bank at Monte Carlo. A few days sooner Mrs. Warren would have been crowded out of their papers by an exceptionally abominable police case. I do not suggest that the police case should have been suppressed; but neither do I believe that regard for public morality had anything to do with their failure to grapple with the performance by the Stage Society. And, after all, there was no need to fall back on Silas Wegg’s subterfuge. Several critics saved the faces of their papers easily enough by the simple expedient of saying all they had to say in the tone of a shocked governess lecturing a naughty child. To them I might plead, in Mrs. Warren’s words, “Well, it’s only good manners to be ashamed, dearie;” but it surprises me, recollecting as I do the effect produced by Miss Fanny Brough’s delivery of that line, that gentlemen who shivered like violets in a zephyr as it swept through them, should so completely miss the full width of its application as to go home and straightway make a public exhibition of mock modesty.

My old Independent Theatre manager, Mr. Grein, besides that reproach to me for shattering his ideals, complains that Mrs. Warren is not wicked enough, and names several romancers who would have clothed her black soul with all the terrors of tragedy. I have no doubt they would; but if you please, my dear Grein, that is just what I did not want to do. Nothing would please our sanctimonious British public more than to throw the whole guilt of Mrs. Warren’s profession on Mrs. Warren herself. Now the whole aim of my play is to throw that guilt on the British public itself. You may remember that when you produced my first play, Widowers’ Houses, exactly the same misunderstanding arose. When the virtuous young gentleman rose up in wrath against the slum landlord, the slum landlord very effectively showed him that slums are the product, not of individual Harpagons, but of the indifference of virtuous young gentlemen to the condition of the city they live in, provided they live at the west end of it on money earned by someone else’s labor. The notion that prostitution is created by the wickedness of Mrs. Warren is as silly as the notion—prevalent, nevertheless, to some extent in Temperance circles—that drunkenness is created by the wickedness of the publican. Mrs. Warren is not a whit a worse woman than the reputable daughter who cannot endure her. Her indifference to the ultimate social consequences of her means of making money, and her discovery of that means by the ordinary method of taking the line of least resistance to getting it, are too common in English society to call for any special remark. Her vitality, her thrift, her energy, her outspokenness, her wise care of her daughter, and the managing capacity which has enabled her and her sister to climb from the fried fish shop down by the Mint to the establishments of which she boasts, are all high English social virtues. Her defence of herself is so overwhelming that it provokes the St. James Gazette to declare that “the tendency of the play is wholly evil” because “it contains one of the boldest and most specious defences of an immoral life for poor women that has ever been penned.” Happily the St. James Gazette here speaks in its haste. Mrs. Warren’s defence of herself is not only bold and specious, but valid and unanswerable. But it is no defence at all of the vice which she organizes. It is no defence of an immoral life to say that the alternative offered by society collectively to poor women is a miserable life, starved, overworked, fetid, ailing, ugly. Though it is quite natural and right for Mrs. Warren to choose what is, according to her lights, the least immoral alternative, it is none the less infamous of society to offer such alternatives. For the alternatives offered are not morality and immorality, but two sorts of immorality. The man who cannot see that starvation, overwork, dirt, and disease are as antisocial as prostitution—that they are the vices and crimes of a nation, and not merely its misfortunes—is (to put it as politely as possible) a hopelessly Private Person.

The notion that Mrs. Warren must be a fiend is only an example of the violence and passion which the slightest reference to sex arouses in undisciplined minds, and which makes it seem natural for our lawgivers to punish silly and negligible indecencies with a ferocity unknown in dealing with, for example, ruinous financial swindling. Had my play been titled Mr. Warren’s Profession, and Mr. Warren been a bookmaker, nobody would have expected me to make him a villain as well. Yet gambling is a vice, and bookmaking an institution, for which there is absolutely nothing to be said. The moral and economic evil done by trying to get other people’s money without working for it (and this is the essence of gambling) is not only enormous but uncompensated. There are no two sides to the question of gambling, no circumstances which force us to tolerate it lest its suppression lead to worse things, no consensus of opinion among responsible classes, such as magistrates and military commanders, that it is a necessity, no Athenian records of gambling made splendid by the talents of its professors, no contention that instead of violating morals it only violates a legal institution which is in many respects oppressive and unnatural, no possible plea that the instinct on which it is founded is a vital one. Prostitution can confuse the issue with all these excuses: gambling has none of them. Consequently, if Mrs. Warren must needs be a demon, a bookmaker must be a cacodemon. Well, does anybody who knows the sporting world really believe that bookmakers are worse than their neighbors? On the contrary, they have to be a good deal better; for in that world nearly everybody whose social rank does not exclude such an occupation would be a bookmaker if he could; but the strength of character for handling large sums of money and for strict settlements and unflinching payment of losses is so rare that successful bookmakers are rare too. It may seem that at least public spirit cannot be one of a bookmaker’s virtues; but I can testify from personal experience that excellent public work is done with money subscribed by bookmakers. It is true that there are abysses in bookmaking: for example, welshing. Mr. Grein hints that there are abysses in Mrs. Warren’s profession also. So there are in every profession: the error lies in supposing that every member of them sounds these depths. I sit on a public body which prosecutes Mrs. Warren zealously; and I can assure Mr. Grein that she is often leniently dealt with because she has conducted her business “respectably” and held herself above its vilest branches. The degrees in infamy are as numerous and as scrupulously observed as the degrees in the peerage: the moralist’s notion that there are depths at which the moral atmosphere ceases is as delusive as the rich man’s notion that there are no social jealousies or snobberies among the very poor. No: had I drawn Mrs. Warren as a fiend in human form, the very people who now rebuke me for flattering her would probably be the first to deride me for deducing her character logically from occupation instead of observing it accurately in society.

One critic is so enslaved by this sort of logic that he calls my portraiture of the Reverend Samuel Gardner an attack on religion.

According to this view Subaltern Iago is an attack on the army, Sir John Falstaff an attack on knighthood, and King Claudius an attack on royalty. Here again the clamor for naturalness and human feeling, raised by so many critics when they are confronted by the real thing on the stage, is really a clamor for the most mechanical and superficial sort of logic. The dramatic reason for making the clergyman what Mrs. Warren calls “an old stick-in-the-mud,” whose son, in spite of much capacity and charm, is a cynically worthless member of society, is to set up a mordant contrast between him and the woman of infamous profession, with her well brought-up, straightforward, hardworking daughter. The critics who have missed the contrast have doubtless observed often enough that many clergymen are in the Church through no genuine calling, but simply because, in circles which can command preferment, it is the refuge of “the fool of the family”; and that clergymen’s sons are often conspicuous reactionists against the restraints imposed on them in childhood by their father’s profession. These critics must know, too, from history if not from experience, that women as unscrupulous as Mrs. Warren have distinguished themselves as administrators and rulers, both commercially and politically. But both observation and knowledge are left behind when journalists go to the theatre. Once in their stalls, they assume that it is “natural” for clergymen to be saintly, for soldiers to be heroic, for lawyers to be hard-hearted, for sailors to be simple and generous, for doctors to perform miracles with little bottles, and for Mrs. Warren to be a beast and a demon. All this is not only not natural, but not dramatic. A man’s profession only enters into the drama of his life when it comes into conflict with his nature. The result of this conflict is tragic in Mrs. Warren’s case, and comic in the clergyman’s case (at least we are savage enough to laugh at it); but in both cases it is illogical, and in both cases natural. I repeat, the critics who accuse me of sacrificing nature to logic are so sophisticated by their profession that to them logic is nature, and nature absurdity.

Many friendly critics are too little skilled in social questions and moral discussions to be able to conceive that respectable gentlemen like themselves, who would instantly call the police to remove Mrs. Warren if she ventured to canvass them personally, could possibly be in any way responsible for her proceedings. They remonstrate sincerely, asking me what good such painful exposures can possibly do. They might as well ask what good Lord Shaftesbury did by devoting his life to the exposure of evils (by no means yet remedied) compared to which the worst things brought into view or even into surmise by this play are trifles. The good of mentioning them is that you make people so extremely uncomfortable about them that they finally stop blaming “human nature” for them, and begin to support measures for their reform.

Can anything be more absurd than the copy of The Echo which contains a notice of the performance of my play? It is edited by a gentleman who, having devoted his life to work of the Shaftesbury type, exposes social evils and clamors for their reform in every column except one; and that one is occupied by the declaration of the paper’s kindly theatre critic, that the performance left him “wondering what useful purpose the play was intended to serve.” The balance has to be redressed by the more fashionable papers, which usually combine capable art criticism with West-End solecism on politics and sociology. It is very noteworthy, however, on comparing the press explosion produced by Mrs. Warren’s Profession in 1902 with that produced by Widowers’ Houses about ten years earlier, that whereas in 1892 the facts were frantically denied and the persons of the drama flouted as monsters of wickedness, in 1902 the facts are admitted and the characters recognized, though it is suggested that this is exactly why no gentleman should mention them in public. Only one writer has ventured to imply this time that the poverty mentioned by Mrs. Warren has since been quietly relieved, and need not have been dragged back to the footlights. I compliment him on his splendid mendacity, in which he is unsupported, save by a little plea in a theatrical paper which is innocent enough to think that ten guineas a year with board and lodging is an impossibly low wage for a barmaid. It goes on to cite Mr. Charles Booth as having testified that there are many laborers’ wives who are happy and contented on eighteen shillings a week. But I can go further than that myself. I have seen an Oxford agricultural laborer’s wife looking cheerful on eight shillings a week; but that does not console me for the fact that agriculture in England is a ruined industry. If poverty does not matter as long as it is contented, then crime does not matter as long as it is unscrupulous. The truth is that it is only then that it does matter most desperately. Many persons are more comfortable when they are dirty than when they are clean; but that does not recommend dirt as a national policy.

Here I must for the present break off my arduous work of educating the Press. We shall resume our studies later on; but just now I am tired of playing the preceptor; and the eager thirst of my pupils for improvement does not console me for the slowness of their progress. Besides, I must reserve space to gratify my own vanity and do justice to the six artists who acted my play, by placing on record the hitherto unchronicled success of the first representation. It is not often that an author, after a couple of hours of those rare alternations of excitement and intensely attentive silence which only occur in the theatre when actors and audience are reacting on one another to the utmost, is able to step on the stage and apply the strong word genius to the representation with the certainty of eliciting an instant and overwhelming assent from the audience. That was my good fortune on the afternoon of Sunday, the fifth of January last. I was certainly extremely fortunate in my interpreters in the enterprise, and that not alone in respect of their artistic talent; for had it not been for their superhuman patience, their imperturbable good humor and good fellowship, there could have been no performance. The terror of the Censor’s power gave us trouble enough to break up any ordinary commercial enterprise. Managers promised and even engaged their theatres to us after the most explicit warnings that the play was unlicensed, and at the last moment suddenly realized that Mr. Redford had their livelihoods in the hollow of his hand, and backed out. Over and over again the date and place were fixed and the tickets printed, only to be canceled, until at last the desperate and overworked manager of the Stage Society could only laugh, as criminals broken on the wheel used to laugh at the second stroke. We rehearsed under great difficulties. Christmas pieces and plays for the new year were being produced in all directions; and my six actor colleagues were busy people, with engagements in these pieces in addition to their current professional work every night. On several raw winter days stages for rehearsal were unattainable even by the most distinguished applicants; and we shared corridors and saloons with them whilst the stage was given over to children in training for Boxing night. At last we had to rehearse at an hour at which no actor or actress has been out of bed within the memory of man; and we sardonically congratulated one another every morning on our rosy matutinal looks and the improvement wrought by our early rising in our health and characters. And all this, please observe, for a society without treasury or commercial prestige, for a play which was being denounced in advance as unmentionable, for an author without influence at the fashionable theatres! I victoriously challenge the West End managers to get as much done for interested motives, if they can.

Three causes made the production the most notable that has fallen to my lot. First, the veto of the Censor, which put the supporters of the play on their mettle. Second, the chivalry of the Stage Society, which, in spite of my urgent advice to the contrary, and my demonstration of the difficulties, dangers, and expenses the enterprise would cost, put my discouragements to shame and resolved to give battle at all costs to the attempt of the Censorship to suppress the play. Third, the artistic spirit of the actors, who made the play their own and carried it through triumphantly in spite of a series of disappointments and annoyances much more trying to the dramatic temperament than mere difficulties.

The acting, too, required courage and character as well as skill and intelligence. The veto of the Censor introduced quite a novel element of moral responsibility into the undertaking. And the characters were very unusual on the English stage. The younger heroine is, like her mother, an Englishwoman to the backbone, and not, like the heroines of our fashionable drama, a prima donna of Italian origin. Consequently she was sure to be denounced as unnatural and undramatic by the critics. The most vicious man in the play is not in the least a stage villain; indeed, he regards his own moral character with the sincere complacency of a hero of melodrama. The amiable devotee of romance and beauty is shown at an age which brings out the futilization which these worships are apt to produce if they are made the staple of life instead of the sauce. The attitude of the clever young people to their elders is faithfully represented as one of pitiless ridicule and unsympathetic criticism, and forms a spectacle incredible to those who, when young, were not cleverer than their nearest elders, and painful to those sentimental parents who shrink from the cruelty of youth, which pardons nothing because it knows nothing. In short, the characters and their relations are of a kind that the routineer critic has not yet learned to place; so that their misunderstanding was a foregone conclusion. Nevertheless, there was no hesitation behind the curtain. When it went up at last, a stage much too small for the company was revealed to an auditorium much too small for the audience. But the players, though it was impossible for them to forget their own discomfort, at once made the spectators forget theirs. It certainly was a model audience, responsive from the first line to the last; and it got no less than it deserved in return.

I grieve to add that the second performance, given for the edification of the London Press and of those members of the Stage Society who cannot attend the Sunday performances, was a less inspiriting one than the first. A solid phalanx of theatre-weary journalists in an afternoon humor, most of them committed to irreconcilable disparagement of problem plays, and all of them bound by etiquette to be as undemonstrative as possible, is not exactly the sort of audience that rises at the performers and cures them of the inevitable reaction after an excitingly successful first night. The artist nature is a sensitive and therefore a vindictive one; and masterful players have a way with recalcitrant audiences of rubbing a play into them instead of delighting them with it. I should describe the second performance of Mrs. Warren’s Profession, especially as to its earlier stages, as decidedly a rubbed-in one. The rubbing was no doubt salutary; but it must have hurt some of the thinner skins. The charm of the lighter passages fled; and the strong scenes, though they again carried everything before them, yet discharged that duty in a grim fashion, doing execution on the enemy rather than moving them to repentance and confession. Still, to those who had not seen the first performance, the effect was sufficiently impressive; and they had the advantage of witnessing a fresh development in Mrs. Warren, who, artistically jealous, as I took it, of the overwhelming effect of the end of the second act on the previous day, threw herself into the fourth act in quite a new way, and achieved the apparently impossible feat of surpassing herself. The compliments paid to Miss Fanny Brough by the critics, eulogistic as they are, are the compliments of men three-fourths duped as Partridge was duped by Garrick. By much of her acting they were so completely taken in that they did not recognize it as acting at all. Indeed, none of the six players quite escaped this consequence of their own thoroughness. There was a distinct tendency among the less experienced critics to complain of their sentiments and behavior. Naturally, the author does not share that grievance.

Piccard’s Cottage, January 1902.

Act I

Summer afternoon in a cottage garden on the eastern slope of a hill a little south of Haslemere in Surrey. Looking up the hill, the cottage is seen in the left hand corner of the garden, with its thatched roof and porch, and a large latticed window to the left of the porch. A paling completely shuts in the garden, except for a gate on the right. The common rises uphill beyond the paling to the sky line. Some folded canvas garden chairs are leaning against the side bench in the porch. A lady’s bicycle is propped against the wall, under the window. A little to the right of the porch a hammock is slung from two posts. A big canvas umbrella, stuck in the ground, keeps the sun off the hammock, in which a young lady is reading and making notes, her head towards the cottage and her feet towards the gate. In front of the hammock, and within reach of her hand, is a common kitchen chair, with a pile of serious-looking books and a supply of writing paper on it.

A gentleman walking on the common comes into sight from behind the cottage. He is hardly past middle age, with something of the artist about him, unconventionally but carefully dressed, and clean-shaven except for a moustache, with an eager susceptible face and very amiable and considerate manners. He has silky black hair, with waves of grey and white in it. His eyebrows are white, his moustache black. He seems not certain of his way. He looks over the palings; takes stock of the place; and sees the young lady.
The Gentleman | Taking off his hat. I beg your pardon. Can you direct me to Hindhead View—Mrs. Alison’s?
The Young Lady | Glancing up from her book. This is Mrs. Alison’s. She resumes her work.
The Gentleman | Indeed! Perhaps—may I ask are you Miss Vivie Warren?
The Young Lady | Sharply, as she turns on her elbow to get a good look at him. Yes.
The Gentleman | Daunted and conciliatory. I’m afraid I appear intrusive. My name is Praed. Vivie at once throws her books upon the chair, and gets out of the hammock. Oh, pray don’t let me disturb you.
Vivie | Striding to the gate and opening it for him. Come in, Mr. Praed. He comes in. Glad to see you. She proffers her hand and takes his with a resolute and hearty grip. She is an attractive specimen of the sensible, able, highly-educated young middle-class Englishwoman. Age 22. Prompt, strong, confident, self-possessed. Plain businesslike dress, but not dowdy. She wears a chatelaine at her belt, with a fountain pen and a paper knife among its pendants.
Praed | Very kind of you indeed, Miss Warren. She shuts the gate with a vigorous slam. He passes in to the middle of the garden, exercising his fingers, which are slightly numbed by her greeting. Has your mother arrived?
Vivie | Quickly, evidently scenting aggression. Is she coming?
Praed | Surprised. Didn’t you expect us?
Vivie | No.
Praed | Now, goodness me, I hope I’ve not mistaken the day. That would be just like me, you know. Your mother arranged that she was to come down from London and that I was to come over from Horsham to be introduced to you.
Vivie | Not at all pleased. Did she? H’m! My mother has rather a trick of taking me by surprise—to see how I behave myself while she’s away, I suppose. I fancy I shall take my mother very much by surprise one of these days, if she makes arrangements that concern me without consulting me beforehand. She hasn’t come.
Praed | Embarrassed. I’m really very sorry.
Vivie | Throwing off her displeasure. It’s not your fault, Mr. Praed, is it? And I’m very glad you’ve come. You are the only one of my mother’s friends I have ever asked her to bring to see me.
Praed | Relieved and delighted. Oh, now this is really very good of you, Miss Warren!
Vivie | Will you come indoors; or would you rather sit out here and talk?
Praed | It will be nicer out here, don’t you think?
Vivie | Then I’ll go and get you a chair. She goes to the porch for a garden chair.
Praed | Following her. Oh, pray, pray! Allow me. He lays hands on the chair.
Vivie | Letting him take it. Take care of your fingers; theyre rather dodgy things, those chairs. She goes across to the chair with the books on it; pitches them into the hammock; and brings the chair forward with one swing.
Praed | Who has just unfolded his chair. Oh, now do let me take that hard chair. I like hard chairs.
Vivie | So do I. Sit down, Mr. Praed. This invitation she gives with a genial peremptoriness, his anxiety to please her clearly striking her as a sign of weakness of character on his part. But he does not immediately obey.
Praed | By the way, though, hadn’t we better go to the station to meet your mother?
Vivie | Coolly. Why? She knows the way. Praed hesitates, and then sits down in the garden chair, rather disconcerted. Do you know, you are just like what I expected. I hope you are disposed to be friends with me?
Praed | Again beaming. Thank you, my dear Miss Warren; thank you. Dear me! I’m so glad your mother hasn’t spoilt you!
Vivie | How?
Praed | Well, in making you too conventional. You know, my dear Miss Warren, I am a born anarchist. I hate authority. It spoils the relations between parent and child; even between mother and daughter. Now I was always afraid that your mother would strain her authority to make you very conventional. It’s such a relief to find that she hasn’t.
Vivie | Oh! have I been behaving unconventionally?
Praed | Oh, no: oh, dear no. At least, not conventionally unconventionally, you understand. She nods and sits down. He goes on, with a cordial outburst. But it was so charming of you to say that you were disposed to be friends with me! You modern young ladies are splendid: perfectly splendid!
Vivie | Dubiously. Eh? Watching him with dawning disappointment as to the quality of his brains and character.
Praed | When I was your age, young men and women were afraid of each other: there was no good fellowship. Nothing real. Only gallantry copied out of novels, and as vulgar and affected as it could be. Maidenly reserve! gentlemanly chivalry! always saying no when you meant yes! simple purgatory for shy and sincere souls.
Vivie | Yes, I imagine there must have been a frightful waste of time. Especially women’s time.
Praed | Oh, waste of life, waste of everything. But things are improving. Do you know, I have been in a positive state of excitement about meeting you ever since your magnificent achievements at Cambridge: a thing unheard of in my day. It was perfectly splendid, your tieing with the third wrangler. Just the right place, you know. The first wrangler is always a dreamy, morbid fellow, in whom the thing is pushed to the length of a disease.
Vivie | It doesn’t pay. I wouldn’t do it again for the same money.
Praed | Aghast. The same money!
Vivie | I did it for fifty pounds. Perhaps you don’t know how it was. Mrs. Latham, my tutor at Newnham, told my mother that I could distinguish myself in the mathematical tripos if I went in for it in earnest. The papers were full just then of Phillipa Summers beating the senior wrangler—you remember about it; and nothing would please my mother but that I should do the same thing. I said flatly that it was not worth my while to face the grind since I was not going in for teaching; but I offered to try for fourth wrangler or thereabouts for fifty pounds. She closed with me at that, after a little grumbling; and I was better than my bargain. But I wouldn’t do it again for that. Two hundred pounds would have been nearer the mark.
Praed | Much damped. Lord bless me! Thats a very practical way of looking at it.
Vivie | Did you expect to find me an unpractical person?
Praed | No, no. But surely it’s practical to consider not only the work these honors cost, but also the culture they bring.
Vivie | Culture! My dear Mr. Praed: do you know what the mathematical tripos means? It means grind, grind, grind for six to eight hours a day at mathematics, and nothing but mathematics. I’m supposed to know something about science; but I know nothing except the mathematics it involves. I can make calculations for engineers, electricians, insurance companies, and so on; but I know next to nothing about engineering or electricity or insurance. I don’t even know arithmetic well. Outside mathematics, lawn-tennis, eating, sleeping, cycling, and walking, I’m a more ignorant barbarian than any woman could possibly be who hadn’t gone in for the tripos.
Praed | Revolted. What a monstrous, wicked, rascally system! I knew it! I felt at once that it meant destroying all that makes womanhood beautiful!
Vivie | I don’t object to it on that score in the least. I shall turn it to very good account, I assure you.
Praed | Pooh! In what way?
Vivie | I shall set up chambers in the city and work at actuarial calculations and conveyancing. Under cover of that I shall do some law, with one eye on the Stock Exchange all the time. I’ve come down here by myself to read law—not for a holiday, as my mother imagines. I hate holidays.
Praed | You make my blood run cold. Are you to have no romance, no beauty in your life?
Vivie | I don’t care for either, I assure you.
Praed | You can’t mean that.
Vivie | Oh yes I do. I like working and getting paid for it. When I’m tired of working, I like a comfortable chair, a cigar, a little whisky, and a novel with a good detective story in it.
Praed | Rising in a frenzy of repudiation. I don’t believe it. I am an artist; and I can’t believe it: I refuse to believe it. It’s only that you haven’t discovered yet what a wonderful world art can open up to you.
Vivie | Yes I have. Last May I spent six weeks in London with Honoria Fraser. Mamma thought we were doing a round of sightseeing together; but I was really at Honoria’s chambers in Chancery Lane every day, working away at actuarial calculations for her, and helping her as well as a greenhorn could. In the evenings we smoked and talked, and never dreamt of going out except for exercise. And I never enjoyed myself more in my life. I cleared all my expenses and got initiated into the business without a fee in the bargain.
Praed | But bless my heart and soul, Miss Warren, do you call that discovering art?
Vivie | Wait a bit. That wasn’t the beginning. I went up to town on an invitation from some artistic people in Fitzjohn’s Avenu; one of the girls was a Newnham chum. They took me to the National Gallery, to the Opera, and to a concert where the band played all the evening—Beethoven and Wagner and so on. I wouldn’t go through that experience again for anything you could offer me. I held out for civility’s sake until the third day; and then I said, plump out, that I couldn’t stand any more of it, and went off to Chancery Lane. Now you know the sort of perfectly splendid modern young lady I am. How do you think I shall get on with my mother?
Praed | Startled. Well, I hope—er—
Vivie | It’s not so much what you hope as what you believe, that I want to know.
Praed | Well, frankly, I am afraid your mother will be a little disappointed. Not from any shortcoming on your part, you know: I don’t mean that. But you are so different from her ideal.
Vivie | What is her ideal like?
Praed | Well, you must have observed, Miss Warren, that people who are dissatisfied with their own bringing-up generally think that the world would be all right if everybody were to be brought up quite differently. Now your mother’s life has been—er—I suppose you know—
Vivie | I know nothing. Praedis appalled. His consternation grows as she continues. That’s exactly my difficulty. You forget, Mr. Praed, that I hardly know my mother. Since I was a child I have lived in England, at school or at college, or with people paid to take charge of me. I have been boarded out all my life; and my mother has lived in Brussels or Vienna and never let me go to her. I only see her when she visits England for a few days. I don’t complain: it’s been very pleasant; for people have been very good to me; and there has always been plenty of money to make things smooth. But don’t imagine I know anything about my mother. I know far less than you do.
Praed | Very ill at ease. In that case—He stops, quite at a loss. Then, with a forced attempt at gaiety: But what nonsense we are talking! Of course you and your mother will get on capitally. He rises, and looks abroad at the view. What a charming little place you have here!
Vivie | Unmoved. If you think you are doing anything but confirming my worst suspicions by changing the subject like that, you must take me for a much greater fool than I hope I am.
Praed | Your worst suspicions! Oh, pray don’t say that. Now don’t.
Vivie | Why won’t my mother’s life bear being talked about?
Praed | Pray think, Miss Vivie. It is natural that I should have a certain delicacy in talking to my old friend’s daughter about her behind her back. You will have plenty of opportunity of talking about it when she comes. Anxiously. I wonder what is keeping her.
Vivie | No: she won’t talk about it either. Rising. However, I won’t press you. Only, mind this, Mr. Praed, I expect there will be a battle royal when my mother hears of my Chancery Lane project.
Praed | Ruefully. I’m afraid there will.
Vivie | I shall win the battle, because I want nothing but my fare to London to start there tomorrow earning my own living by devilling for Honoria. Besides, I have no mysteries to keep up; and it seems she has. I shall use that advantage over her if necessary.
Praed | Greatly shocked. Oh, no. No, pray. You’d not do such a thing.
Vivie | Then tell me why not.
Praed | I really cannot. I appeal to your good feeling. She smiles at his sentimentality. Besides, you may be too bold. Your mother is not to be trifled with when she’s angry.
Vivie | You can’t frighten me, Mr. Praed. In that month at Chancery Lane I had opportunities of taking the measure of one or two women very like my mother. You may back me to win. But if I hit harder in my ignorance than I need, remember it is you who refuse to enlighten me. Now, let us drop the subject. She takes her chair and replaces it near the hammock with the same vigorous swing as before.
Praed | Taking a desperate resolution. One word, Miss Warren. I had better tell you. It’s very difficult; but—
Mrs. Warren and Sir George Crofts arrive at the gate. Mrs. Warren is between 40 and 50, formerly pretty, showily dressed in a brilliant hat and a gay blouse fitting tightly over her bust and flanked by fashionable sleeves. Rather spoilt and domineering, and decidedly vulgar, but, on the whole, a genial and fairly presentable old blackguard of a woman.
Crofts is a tall powerfully-built man of about 50, fashionably dressed in the style of a young man. Nasal voice, reedier than might be expected from his strong frame. Clean-shaven bulldog jaws, large flat ears, and thick neck: gentlemanly combination of the most brutal types of city man, sporting man, and man about town.
Vivie | Here they are. Coming to them as they enter the garden. How do, mater? Mr. Praed’s been here this half hour, waiting for you.
Mrs. Warren | Well, if you’ve been waiting, Praddy, it’s your own fault: I thought you’d have had the gumption to know I was coming by the 3.10 train. Vivie: put your hat on, dear: you’ll get sunburnt. Oh, I forgot to introduce you. Sir George Crofts: my little Vivie.
Crofts advances to Vivie with his most courtly manner. She nods, but makes no motion to shake hands.
Crofts | May I shake hands with a young lady whom I have known by reputation very long as the daughter of one of my oldest friends?
Vivie | Who has been looking him up and down sharply. If you like. She takes his tenderly proferred hand and gives it a squeeze that makes him open his eyes; then turns away, and says to her mother: Will you come in, or shall I get a couple more chairs? She goes into the porch for the chairs.
Mrs. Warren | Well, George, what do you think of her?
Crofts | Ruefully. She has a powerful fist. Did you shake hands with her, Praed?
Praed | Yes: it will pass off presently.
Crofts | I hope so. Vivie reappears with two more chairs. He hurries to her assistance. Allow me.
Mrs. Warren | Patronizingly. Let Sir George help you with the chairs, dear.
Vivie | Almost pitching two into his arms. Here you are. She dusts her hands and turns to Mrs. Warren. You’d like some tea, wouldn’t you?
Mrs. Warren | Sitting in Praed’s chair and fanning herself. I’m dying for a drop to drink.
Vivie | I’ll see about it. She goes into the cottage. Sir George has by this time managed to unfold a chair and plant it by Mrs. Warren, on her left. He throws the other on the grass and sits down, looking dejected and rather foolish, with the handle of his stick in his mouth. Praed, still very uneasy, fidgets around the garden on their right.
Mrs. Warren | To Praed, looking at Crofts. Just look at him, Praddy: he looks cheerful, don’t he? He’s been worrying my life out these three years to have that little girl of mine shown to him; and now that I’ve done it, he’s quite out of countenance. Briskly. Come! sit up, George; and take your stick out of your mouth. Crofts sulkily obeys.
Praed | I think, you know—if you don’t mind my saying so—that we had better get out of the habit of thinking of her as a little girl. You see she has really distinguished herself; and I’m not sure, from what I have seen of her, that she is not older than any of us.
Mrs. Warren | Greatly amused. Only listen to him, George! Older than any of us! Well, she has been stuffing you nicely with her importance.
Praed | But young people are particularly sensitive about being treated in that way.
Mrs. Warren | Yes; and young people have to get all that nonsense taken out of them, and good deal more besides. Don’t you interfere, Praddy: I know how to treat my own child as well as you do. Praed, with a grave shake of his head, walks up the garden with his hands behind his back. Mrs. Warren pretends to laugh, but looks after him with perceptible concern. Then, she whispers to Crofts: Whats the matter with him? What does he take it like that for?
Crofts | Morosely. You’re afraid of Praed.
Mrs. Warren | What! Me! Afraid of dear old Praddy! Why, a fly wouldn’t be afraid of him.
Crofts | You’re afraid of him.
Mrs. Warren | Angry. I’ll trouble you to mind your own business, and not try any of your sulks on me. I’m not afraid of you, anyhow. If you can’t make yourself agreeable, you’d better go home. She gets up, and, turning her back on him, finds herself face to face with Praed. Come, Praddy, I know it was only your tenderheartedness. You’re afraid I’ll bully her.
Praed | My dear Kitty: you think I’m offended. Don’t imagine that: pray don’t. But you know I often notice things that escape you; and though you never take my advice, you sometimes admit afterwards that you ought to have taken it.
Mrs. Warren | Well, what do you notice now?
Praed | Only that Vivie is a grown woman. Pray, Kitty, treat her with every respect.
Mrs. Warren | With genuine amazement. Respect! Treat my own daughter with respect! What next, pray!
Vivie | Appearing at the cottage door and calling to Mrs. Warren. Mother: will you come to my room before tea?
Mrs. Warren | Yes, dearie. She laughs indulgently at Praed’s gravity, and pats him on the cheek as she passes him on her way to the porch. Don’t be cross, Praddy. She follows Vivie into the cottage.
Crofts | Furtively. I say, Praed.
Praed | Yes.
Crofts | I want to ask you a rather particular question.
Praed | Certainly. He takes Mrs. Warren’s chair and sits close to Crofts.
Crofts | Thats right: they might hear us from the window. Look here: did Kitty every tell you who that girl’s father is?
Praed | Never.
Crofts | Have you any suspicion of who it might be?
Praed | None.
Crofts | Not believing him. I know, of course, that you perhaps might feel bound not to tell if she had said anything to you. But it’s very awkward to be uncertain about it now that we shall be meeting the girl every day. We don’t exactly know how we ought to feel towards her.
Praed | What difference can that make? We take her on her own merits. What does it matter who her father was?
Crofts | Suspiciously. Then you know who he was?
Praed | With a touch of temper. I said no just now. Did you not hear me?
Crofts | Look here, Praed. I ask you as a particular favor. If you do know—movement of protest from Praed—I only say, if you know, you might at least set my mind at rest about her. The fact is, I feel attracted towards her. Oh, don't be alarmed: it's quite an innocent feeling. That's what puzzles me about it. Why, for all I know, I might be her father.
Praed | You! Impossible! Oh, no, nonsense.
Crofts | Catching him up cunningly. You know for certain that I’m not?
Praed | I know nothing about it, I tell you, any more than you. But really, Crofts—oh no, it’s out of the question. Theres not the least resemblance.
Crofts | As to that, theres no resemblance between her and her mother that I can see. I suppose she’s not your daughter, is she?
Praed | (He meets the question with an indignant stare; then recovers himself with an effort and answers gently and gravely. Now listen to me, my dear Crofts. He sits down again. I have nothing to do with that side of Mrs. Warren’s life, and never had. She has never spoken to me about it; and of course I have never spoken to her about it. Your delicacy will tell you that a handsome woman needs some friends who are not—well, not on that footing with her. The effect of her own beauty would become a torment to her if she could not escape from it occasionally. You are probably on much more confidential terms with Kitty than I am. Surely you can ask her the question yourself.
Crofts | Rising impatiently. I have asked her, often enough. But she’s so determined to keep the child all to herself that she would deny that it ever had a father if she could. Rising. I’m thoroughly uncomfortable about it, Praed.
Praed | Rising also. Well, as you are, at all events, old enough to be her father, I don’t mind agreeing that we both regard Miss Vivie in a parental way, as a young girl who we are bound to protect and help. What do you say?
Crofts | Aggressively. I’m no older than you, if you come to that.
Praed | Yes you are, my dear fellow: you were born old. I was born a boy: I’ve never been able to feel the assurance of a grown-up man in my life.
Mrs. Warren | Calling from within the cottage. Prad‑dee! George! Tea‑ea‑ea‑ea!
Crofts | Hastily. She’s calling us. He hurries in. Praed shakes his head bodingly, and is following slowly when he is hailed by a young gentleman who has just appeared on the common, and is making for the gate. He is a pleasant, pretty, smartly dressed, cleverly good-for-nothing young fellow, not long turned 20, with a charming voice and agreeably disrespectful manner. He carries a very light sporting magazine rifle.
The Young Gentleman | Hallo! Praed!
Praed | Why, Frank Gardner! Frank comes in and shakes hands cordially. What on earth are you doing here?
Frank | Staying with my father.
Praed | The Roman father?
Frank | He’s rector here. I’m living with my people this autumn for the sake of economy. Things came to a crisis in July: the Roman father had to pay my debts. He’s stony broke in consequence; and so am I. What are you up to in these parts? Do you know the people here?
Praed | Yes: I’m spending the day with a Miss Warren.
Frank | Enthusiastically. What! Do you know Vivie? Isn’t she a jolly girl? I’m teaching her to shoot—you see! Showing the rifle. I’m so glad she knows you: you’re just the sort of fellow she ought to know. He smiles, and raises the charming voice almost to a singing tone as he exclaims: It’s ever so jolly to find you here, Praed. Ain’t it, now?
Praed | I’m an old friend of her mother. Mrs. Warren brought me over to make her daughter’s acquaintance.
Frank | The mother! Is she here?
Praed | Yes—inside at tea.
Mrs. Warren | Calling from within. Prad‑dee‑ee‑ee‑eee! The teacake’ll be cold.
Praed | Calling. Yes, Mrs. Warren. In a moment. I’ve just met a friend here.
Mrs. Warren | A what?
Praed | Louder. A friend.
Mrs. Warren | Bring him in.
Praed | All right. To Frank. Will you accept the invitation?
Frank | Incredulous, but immensely amused. Is that Vivie’s mother?
Praed | Yes.
Frank | By Jove! What a lark! Do you think she’ll like me?
Praed | I’ve no doubt you’ll make yourself popular, as usual. Come in and try. Moving towards the house.
Frank | Stop a bit. Seriously. I want to take you into my confidence.
Praed | Pray don’t. It’s only some fresh folly, like the barmaid at Redhill.
Frank | It’s ever so much more serious than that. You say you’ve only just met Vivie for the first time?
Praed | Yes.
Frank | Rhapsodically. Then you can have no idea what a girl she is. Such character! Such sense! And her cleverness! Oh, my eye, Praed, but I can tell you she is clever! And—need I add?—she loves me.
Crofts | Putting his head out of the window. I say, Praed: what are you about? Do come along. He disappears.
Frank | Hallo! Sort of chap that would take a prize at a dog show, ain’t he? Who’s he?
Praed | Sir George Crofts, an old friend of Mrs. Warren’s. I think we had better come in.
On their way to the porch they are interrupted by a call from the gate. Turning, they see an elderly clergyman looking over it.
The Clergyman | Calling. Frank!
Frank | Hallo! To Praed. The Roman father. To the clergyman. Yes, gov’nor: all right: presently. To Praed. Look here, Praed: you’d better go in to tea. I’ll join you directly.
Praed | Very good. He goes into the cottage.
The clergyman remains outside the gate, with his hands on the top of it. The Rev. Samuel Gardner, a beneficed clergyman of the Established Church, is over 50. Externally he is pretentious, booming, noisy, important. Really he is that obsolescent phenomenon the fool of the family dumped on the Church by his father the patron, clamorously asserting himself as father and clergyman without being able to command respect in either capacity.
Rev. S. | Well, sir. Who are your friends here, if I may ask?
Frank | Oh, it’s all right, gov’nor! Come in.
Rev. S. | No, sir; not until I know whose garden I am entering.
Frank | It’s all right. It’s Miss Warren’s.
Rev. S. | I have not seen her at church since she came.
Frank | Of course not: she’s a third wrangler. Ever so intellectual. Took a higher degree than you did; so why should she go to hear you preach?
Rev. S. | Don’t be disrespectful, sir.
Frank | Oh, it don’t matter: nobody hears us. Come in. He opens the gate, unceremoniously pulling his father with it into the garden. I want to introduce you to her. Do you remember the advice you gave me last July, gov’nor?
Rev. S. | Severely. Yes. I advised you to conquer your idleness and flippancy, and to work your way into an honorable profession and live on it and not upon me.
Frank | No: thats what you thought of afterwards. What you actually said was that since I had neither brains nor money, I’d better turn my good looks to account by marrying someone with both. Well, look here. Miss Warren has brains: you can’t deny that.
Rev. S. | Brains are not everything.
Frank | No, of course not: theres the money—
Rev. S. | Interrupting him austerely. I was not thinking of money, sir. I was speaking of higher things. Social position, for instance.
Frank | I don’t care a rap about that.
Rev. S. | But I do, sir.
Frank | Well, nobody wants you to marry her. Anyhow, she has what amounts to a high Cambridge degree; and she seems to have as much money as she wants.
Rev. S. | Sinking into a feeble vein of humor. I greatly doubt whether she has as much money as you will want.
Frank | Oh, come: I havn’t been so very extravagant. I live ever so quietly; I don’t drink; I don’t bet much; and I never go regularly to the razzle-dazzle as you did when you were my age.
Rev. S. | Booming hollowly. Silence, sir.
Frank | Well, you told me yourself, when I was making every such an ass of myself about the barmaid at Redhill, that you once offered a woman fifty pounds for the letters you wrote to her when—
Rev. S. | Terrified. Sh-sh-sh, Frank, for Heaven’s sake! He looks round apprehensively Seeing no one within earshot he plucks up courage to boom again, but more subduedly. You are taking an ungentlemanly advantage of what I confided to you for your own good, to save you from an error you would have repented all your life long. Take warning by your father’s follies, sir; and don’t make them an excuse for your own.
Frank | Did you ever hear the story of the Duke of Wellington and his letters?
Rev. S. | No, sir; and I don’t want to hear it.
Frank | The old Iron Duke didn’t throw away fifty pounds: not he. He just wrote: “Dear Jenny: publish and be damned! Yours affectionately, Wellington.” Thats what you should have done.
Rev. S. | Piteously. Frank, my boy: when I wrote those letters I put myself into that woman’s power. When I told you about them I put myself, to some extent, I am sorry to say, in your power. She refused my money with these words, which I shall never forget. “Knowledge is power” she said; “and I never sell power.” Thats more than twenty years ago; and she has never made use of her power or caused me a moment’s uneasiness. You are behaving worse to me than she did, Frank.
Frank | Oh yes I dare say! Did you ever preach at her the way you preach at me every day?
Rev. S. | Wounded almost to tears. I leave you, sir. You are incorrigible. He turns towards the gate.
Frank | Utterly unmoved. Tell them I shan’t be home to tea, will you, gov’nor, like a good fellow? He moves towards the cottage door and is met by Praed and Vivie coming out.
Vivie | To Frank. Is that your father, Frank? I do so want to meet him.
Frank | Certainly. Calling after his father. Gov’nor. You’re wanted. The parson turns at the gate, fumbling nervously at his hat. Praed crosses the garden to the opposite side, beaming in anticipation of civilities. My father: Miss Warren.
Vivie | Going to the clergyman and shaking his hand. Very glad to see you here, Mr. Gardner. Calling to the cottage. Mother: come along: you’re wanted.
Mrs. Warren appears on the threshold, and is immediately transfixed, recognizing the clergyman.
Vivie | Continuing. Let me introduce—
Mrs. Warren | Swooping on the Reverend Samuel. Why it’s Sam Gardner, gone into the Church! Well, I never! Don’t you know us, Sam? This is George Crofts, as large as life and twice as natural. Don’t you remember me?
Rev. S. | Very red. I really—er—
Mrs. Warren | Of course you do. Why, I have a whole album of your letters still: I came across them only the other day.
Rev. S. | Miserably confused. Miss Vavasour, I believe.
Mrs. Warren | Correcting him quickly in a loud whisper. Tch! Nonsense! Mrs. Warren: don’t you see my daughter there?

Act III

In the Rectory garden next morning, with the sun shining from a cloudless sky. The garden wall has a five-barred wooden gate, wide enough to admit a carriage, in the middle. Beside the gate hangs a bell on a coiled spring, communicating with a pull outside. The carriage drive comes down the middle of the garden and then swerves to its left, where it ends in a little gravelled circus opposite the Rectory porch. Beyond the gate is seen the dusty high road, parallel with the wall, bounded on the farther side by a strip of turf and an unfenced pine wood. On the lawn, between the house and the drive, is a clipped yew tree, with a garden bench in its shade. On the opposite side the garden is shut in by a box hedge; and there is a little sundial on the turf, with an iron chair near it. A little path leads through the box hedge, behind the sundial. Frank, seated on the chair near the sundial, on which he has placed the morning paper, is reading The Standard. His father comes from the house, red-eyed and shivery, and meets Frank’s eye with misgiving. Frank Looking at his watch. Half-past eleven. Nice hour for a rector to come down to breakfast! Rev S. Don’t mock, Frank: don’t mock. I am a little—er—Shivering— Frank Off color? Rev S. repudiating the expression No, sir: unwell this morning. Where’s your mother? Frank Don’t be alarmed: she’s not here. Gone to town by the 11.13 with Bessie. She left several messages for you. Do you feel equal to receiving them now, or shall I wait til you’ve breakfasted? Rev S. I have breakfasted, sir. I am surprised at your mother going to town when we have people staying with us. They’ll think it very strange. Frank Possibly she has considered that. At all events, if Crofts is going to stay here, and you are going to sit up every night with him until four, recalling the incidents of your fiery youth, it is clearly my mother’s duty, as a prudent housekeeper, to go up to the stores and order a barrel of whisky and a few hundred siphons. Rev S. I did not observe that Sir George drank excessively. Frank You were not in a condition to, gov’nor. Rev S. Do you mean to say that I—? Frank Calmly. I never saw a beneficed clergyman less sober. The anecdotes you told about your past career were so awful that I really don’t think Praed would have passed the night under your roof if it hadnt been for the way my mother and he took to one another. Rev S. Nonsense, sir. I am Sir George Crofts’ host. I must talk to him about something; and he has only one subject. Where is Mr. Praed now? Frank He is driving my mother and Bessie to the station. Rev S. Is Crofts up yet? Frank Oh, long ago. He hasn’t turned a hair: he’s in much better practice than you. Has kept it up ever since, probably. He’s taken himself off somewhere to smoke. Frank resumes his paper. The parson turns disconsolately towards the gate; then comes back irresolutely. Rev S. Er—Frank. Frank Yes. Rev S. Do you think the Warrens will expect to be asked here after yesterday afternoon? Frank Theyve been asked already. Rev S. appalled What!!! Frank Crofts informed us at breakfast that you told him to bring Mrs. Warren and Vivie over here to-day, and to invite them to make this house their home. My mother then found she must go to town by the 11.13 train. Rev S. with despairing vehemence I never gave any such invitation. I never thought of such a thing. Frank Compassionately. How do you know, gov’nor, what you said and thought last night? Praed Coming in through the hedge. Good morning. Rev S. Good morning. I must apologize for not having met you at breakfast. I have a touch of—of— Frank Clergyman’s sore throat, Praed. Fortunately not chronic. Praed Changing the subject. Well I must say your house is in a charming spot here. Really most charming. Rev S. Yes: it is indeed. Frank will take you for a walk, Mr. Praed, if you like. I’ll ask you to excuse me: I must take the opportunity to write my sermon while Mrs. Gardner is away and you are all amusing yourselves. You won’t mind, will you? Praed Certainly not. Don’t stand on the slightest ceremony with me. Rev S. Thank you. I’ll—er—er—He stammers his way to the porch and vanishes into the house. Praed Curious thing it must be writing a sermon every week. Frank Ever so curious, if he did it. He buys em. He’s gone for some soda water. Praed My dear boy: I wish you would be more respectful to your father. You know you can be so nice when you like. Frank My dear Praddy: you forget that I have to live with the governor. When two people live together—it don’t matter whether theyre father and son or husband and wife or brother and sister—they can’t keep up the polite humbug thats so easy for ten minutes on an afternoon call. Now the governor, who unites to many admirable domestic qualities the irresoluteness of a sheep and the pompousness and aggressiveness of a jackass— Praed No, pray, pray, my dear Frank, remember! He is your father. Frank I give him due credit for that. Rising and flinging down his paper But just imagine his telling Crofts to bring the Warrens over here! He must have been ever so drunk. You know, my dear Praddy, my mother wouldn’t stand Mrs. Warren for a moment. Vivie mustn’t come here until she’s gone back to town. Praed But your mother doesn’t know anything about Mrs. Warren, does she? He picks up the paper and sits down to read it. Frank I don’t know. Her journey to town looks as if she did. Not that my mother would mind in the ordinary way: she has stuck like a brick to lots of women who had got into trouble. But they were all nice women. Thats what makes the real difference. Mrs. Warren, no doubt, has her merits; but she’s ever so rowdy; and my mother simply wouldn’t put up with her. So—hallo! This exclamation is provoked by the reappearance of the clergyman, who comes out of the house in haste and dismay. Rev S. Frank: Mrs. Warren and her daughter are coming across the heath with Crofts: I saw them from the study windows. What am I to say about your mother? Frank Stick on your hat and go out and say how delighted you are to see them; and that Frank’s in the garden; and that mother and Bessie have been called to the bedside of a sick relative, and were ever so sorry they couldn’t stop; and that you hope Mrs. Warren slept well; and—and—say any blessed thing except the truth, and leave the rest to Providence. Rev S. But how are we to get rid of them afterwards? Frank Theres no time to think of that now. Here! He bounds into the house. Rev S. He’s so impetuous. I don’t know what to do with him, Mr. Praed. Frank Returning with a clerical felt hat, which he claps on his father’s head. Now: off with you. Rushing him through the gate. Praed and I’ll wait here, to give the thing an unpremeditated air. The clergyman, dazed but obedient, hurries off. Frank We must get the old girl back to town somehow, Praed. Come! Honestly, dear Praddy, do you like seeing them together? Praed Oh, why not? Frank His teeth on edge. Don’t it make your flesh creep ever so little? that wicked old devil, up to every villainy under the sun, I’ll swear, and Vivie—ugh! Praed Hush, pray. Theyre coming. The clergyman and Crofts are seen coming along the road, followed by Mrs. Warren and Vivie walking affectionately together. Frank Look: she actually has her arm round the old woman’s waist. It’s her right arm: she began it. She’s gone sentimental, by God! Ugh! ugh! Now do you feel the creeps? The clergyman opens the gate: and Mrs. Warren and Vivie pass him and stand in the middle of the garden looking at the house. Frank, in an ecstasy of dissimulation, turns gaily to Mrs. Warren, exclaiming Ever so delighted to see you, Mrs. Warren. This quiet old rectory garden becomes you perfectly. Mrs. Warren Well, I never! Did you hear that, George? He says I look well in a quiet old rectory garden. Rev S. still holding the gate for Crofts, who loafs through it, heavily bored You look well everywhere, Mrs. Warren. Frank Bravo, gov’nor! Now look here: lets have a treat before lunch. First lets see the church. Everyone has to do that. It’s a regular old thirteenth century church, you know: the gov’nor’s ever so fond of it, because he got up a restoration fund and had it completely rebuilt six years ago. Praed will be able to shew its points. Praed Rising. Certainly, if the restoration has left any to shew. Rev S. mooning hospitably at them I shall be pleased, I’m sure, if Sir George and Mrs. Warren really care about it. Mrs. Warren Oh, come along and get it over. Crofts Turning back toward the gate. I’ve no objection. Rev S. Not that way. We go through the fields, if you don’t mind. Round here. He leads the way by the little path through the box hedge. Crofts Oh, all right. He goes with the parson. Praed follows with Mrs. Warren. Vivie does not stir: she watches them until they have gone, with all the lines of purpose in her face marking it strongly. Frank Ain’t you coming? Vivie No. I want to give you a warning, Frank. You were making fun of my mother just now when you said that about the rectory garden. That is barred in the future. Please treat my mother with as much respect as you treat your own. Frank My dear Viv: she wouldn’t appreciate it: the two cases require different treatment. But what on earth has happened to you? Last night we were perfectly agreed as to your mother and her set. This morning I find you attitudinizing sentimentally with your arm around your parent’s waist. Vivie Flushing. Attitudinizing! Frank That was how it struck me. First time I ever saw you do a second-rate thing. Vivie Controlling herself. Yes, Frank: there has been a change: but I don’t think it a change for the worse. Yesterday I was a little prig. Frank And today? Vivie Wincing; then looking at him steadily. Today I know my mother better than you do. Frank Heaven forbid! Vivie What do you mean? Frank Viv: theres a freemasonry among thoroughly immoral people that you know nothing of. You’ve too much character. That’s the bond between your mother and me: that’s why I know her better than youll ever know her. Vivie You are wrong: you know nothing about her. If you knew the circumstances against which my mother had to struggle— Frank Adroitly finishing the sentence for her. I should know why she is what she is, shouldn’t I? What difference would that make? Circumstances or no circumstances, Viv, you won’t be able to stand your mother. Vivie Very angry. Why not? Frank Because she’s an old wretch, Viv. If you ever put your arm around her waist in my presence again, I’ll shoot myself there and then as a protest against an exhibition which revolts me. Vivie Must I choose between dropping your acquaintance and dropping my mother’s? Frank Gracefully. That would put the old lady at ever such a disadvantage. No, Viv: your infatuated little boy will have to stick to you in any case. But he’s all the more anxious that you shouldn’t make mistakes. It’s no use, Viv: your mother’s impossible. She may be a good sort; but she’s a bad lot, a very bad lot. Vivie Hotly. Frank—! He stands his ground. She turns away and sits down on the bench under the yew tree, struggling to recover her self-command. Then she says Is she to be deserted by the world because she’s what you call a bad lot? Has she no right to live? Frank No fear of that, Viv: she won’t ever be deserted. He sits on the bench beside her. Vivie But I am to desert her, I suppose. Frank Babyishly, lulling her and making love to her with his voice. Mustn’t go live with her. Little family group of mother and daughter wouldn’t be a success. Spoil our little group. Vivie Falling under the spell. What little group? Frank The babes in the wood: Vivie and little Frank. He nestles against her like a weary child. Lets go and get covered up with leaves. Vivie Rhythmically, rocking him like a nurse. Fast asleep, hand in hand, under the trees. Frank The wise little girl with her silly little boy. Vivie The dear little boy with his dowdy little girl. Frank Ever so peaceful, and relieved from the imbecility of the little boy’s father and the questionableness of the little girl’s— Vivie Smothering the word against her breast Sh-sh-sh-sh! little girl wants to forget all about her mother. They are silent for some moments, rocking one another. Then Vivie wakes up with a shock, exclaiming What a pair of fools we are! Come: sit up. Gracious! your hair. She smooths it. I wonder do all grown up people play in that childish way when nobody is looking. I never did it when I was a child. Frank Neither did I. You are my first playmate. He catches her hand to kiss it, but checks himself to look around first. Very unexpectedly, he sees Crofts emerging from the box hedge. Oh damn! Vivie Why damn, dear? Frank Whispering Sh! Here’s this brute Crofts. He sits farther away from her with an unconcerned air. Crofts Could I have a few words with you, Miss Vivie? Vivie Certainly. Crofts To Frank. Youll excuse me, Gardner. Theyre waiting for you in the church, if you don’t mind. Frank Rising Anything to oblige you, Crofts—except church. If you should happen to want me, Vivvums, ring the gate bell. He goes into the house with unruffled suavity. Crofts Watching him with a crafty air as he disappears, and speaking to Vivie with an assumption of being on privileged terms with her. Pleasant young fellow that, Miss Vivie. Pity he has no money, isn’t it? Vivie Do you think so? Crofts Well, whats he to do? No profession. No property. Whats he good for? Vivie I realize his disadvantages, Sir George. Crofts A little taken aback at being so precisely interpreted Oh, it’s not that. But while we’re in this world we’re in it; and money’s money. Vivie does not answer. Nice day, isn’t it? Vivie With scarcely veiled contempt for this effort at conversation. Very. Crofts With brutal good humor, as if he liked her pluck. Well thats not what I came to say. Sitting down beside her Now listen, Miss Vivie. I’m quite aware that I’m not a young lady’s man. Vivie Indeed, Sir George? Crofts No; and to tell you the honest truth I don’t want to be either. But when I say a thing I mean it; and when I feel a sentiment I feel it in earnest; and what I value I pay hard money for. Thats the sort of man I am. Vivie It does you great credit, I’m sure. Crofts Oh, I don’t mean to praise myself. I have my faults, Heaven knows: no man is more sensible of that than I am. I know I’m not perfect: thats one of the advantages of being a middle-aged man; for I’m not a young man, and I know it. But my code is a simple one, and, I think, a good one. Honor between man and man; fidelity between man and woman; and no can’t about this religion or that religion, but an honest belief that things are making for good on the whole. Vivie With biting irony. “A power, not ourselves, that makes for righteousness,” eh? Crofts Taking her seriously. Oh certainly. Not ourselves, of course. Y o u understand what I mean. Well, now as to practical matters. You may have an idea that I’ve flung my money about; but I havn’t: I’m richer today than when I first came into the property. I’ve used my knowledge of the world to invest my money in ways that other men have overlooked; and whatever else I may be, I’m a safe man from the money point of view. Vivie It’s very kind of you to tell me all this. Crofts Oh well, come, Miss Vivie: you needn’t pretend you don’t see what I’m driving at. I want to settle down with a Lady Crofts. I suppose you think me very blunt, eh? Vivie Not at all: I am very much obliged to you for being so definite and business-like. I quite appreciate the offer: the money, the position, Lady Crofts, and so on. But I think I will say no, if you don’t mind, I’d rather not. She rises, and strolls across to the sundial to get out of his immediate neighborhood. Crofts Not at all discouraged, and taking advantage of the additional room left him on the seat to spread himself comfortably, as if a few preliminary refusals were part of the inevitable routine of courtship. I’m in no hurry. It was only just to let you know in case young Gardner should try to trap you. Leave the question open. Vivie Sharply. My no is final. I won’t go back from it. Crofts is not impressed. He grins; leans forward with his elbows on his knees to prod with his stick at some unfortunate insect in the grass; and looks cunningly at her. She turns away impatiently. Crofts I’m a good deal older than you. Twenty-five years: quarter of a century. I shan’t live for ever; and I’ll take care that you shall be well off when I’m gone. Vivie I am proof against even that inducement, Sir George. Don’t you think youd better take your answer? There is not the slightest chance of my altering it. Crofts Rising, after a final slash at a daisy, and coming nearer to her. Well, no matter. I could tell you some things that would change your mind fast enough; but I wont, because I’d rather win you by honest affection. I was a good friend to your mother: ask her whether I wasn’t. She’d never have make the money that paid for your education if it hadnt been for my advice and help, not to mention the money I advanced her. There are not many men who would have stood by her as I have. I put not less than forty thousand pounds into it, from first to last. Vivie Staring at him. Do you mean to say that you were my mother’s business partner? Crofts Yes. Now just think of all the trouble and the explanations it would save if we were to keep the whole thing in the family, so to speak. Ask your mother whether she’d like to have to explain all her affairs to a perfect stranger. Vivie I see no difficulty, since I understand that the business is wound up, and the money invested. Crofts Stopping short, amazed. Wound up! Wind up a business thats paying 35 per cent in the worst years! Not likely. Who told you that? Vivie Her color quite gone Do you mean that it is still—? She stops abruptly, and puts her hand on the sundial to support herself. Then she gets quickly to the iron chair and sits down. What business are you talking about? Crofts Well, the fact is it’s not what would considered exactly a high-class business in my set—the country set, you know—our set it will be if you think better of my offer. Not that theres any mystery about it: don’t think that. Of course you know by your mother’s being in it that it’s perfectly straight and honest. I’ve known her for many years; and I can say of her that she’d cut off her hands sooner than touch anything that was not what it ought to be. I’ll tell you all about it if you like. I don’t know whether you’ve found in travelling how hard it is to find a really comfortable private hotel. Vivie Sickened, averting her face. Yes: go on. Crofts Well, thats all it is. Your mother has got a genius for managing such things. We’ve got two in Brussels, one in Ostend, one in Vienna, and two in Budapest. Of course there are others besides ourselves in it; but we hold most of the capital; and your mother’s indispensable as managing director. You’ve noticed, I daresay, that she travels a good deal. But you see you can’t mention such things in society. Once let out the word hotel and everybody thinks you keep a public-house. You wouldn’t like people to say that of your mother, would you? Thats why we’re so reserved about it. By the way, youll keep it to yourself, won’t you? Since it’s been a secret so long, it had better remain so. Vivie And this is the business you invite me to join you in? Crofts Oh no. My wife shan’t be troubled with business. Youll not be in it more than you’ve always been. Vivie I always been! What do you mean? Crofts Only that you’ve always lived on it. It paid for your education and the dress you have on your back. Don’t turn up your nose at business, Miss Vivie: where would your Newnhams and Girtons be without it? Vivie Rising, almost beside herself. Take care. I know what this business is. Crofts Starting, with a suppressed oath. Who told you? Vivie Your partner. My mother. Crofts Black with rage. The old— Vivie Just so. He swallows the epithet and stands for a moment swearing and raging foully to himself. But he knows that his cue is to be sympathetic. He takes refuge in generous indignation. Crofts She ought to have had more consideration for you. I’d never have told you. Vivie I think you would probably have told me when we were married: it would have been a convenient weapon to break me in with. Crofts Quite sincerely. I never intended that. On my word as a gentleman I didn’t. Vivie wonders at him. Her sense of the irony of his protest cools and braces her. She replies with contemptuous self-possession. Vivie It does not matter. I suppose you understand that when we leave here today our acquaintance ceases. Crofts Why? Is it for helping your mother? Vivie My mother was a very poor woman who had no reasonable choice but to do as she did. You were a rich gentleman; and you did the same for the sake of 35 per cent. You are a pretty common sort of scoundrel, I think. That is my opinion of you. Crofts After a stare: not at all displeased, and much more at his ease on these frank terms than on their former ceremonious ones. Ha! ha! ha! ha! Go it, little missie, go it: it doesn’t hurt me and it amuses you. Why the devil shouldn’t I invest my money that way? I take the interest on my capital like other people: I hope you don’t think I dirty my own hands with the work. Come! you wouldn’t refuse the acquaintance of my mother’s cousin the Duke of Belgravia because some of the rents he gets are earned in queer ways. You wouldn’t cut the Archbishop of Canterbury, I suppose, because the Ecclesiastical Commissioners have a few publicans and sinners among their tenants. Do you remember your Crofts scholarship at Newnham? Well, that was founded by my brother the M.P. He gets his 22 per cent out of a factory with 600 girls in it, and not one of them getting wages enough to live on. How d’ye suppose they manage when they have no family to fall back on? Ask your mother. And do you expect me to turn my back on 35 per cent when all the rest are pocketing what they can, like sensible men? No such fool! If youre going to pick and choose your acquaintances on moral principles, youd better clear out of this country, unless you want to cut yourself out of all decent society. Vivie Conscience stricken. You might go on to point out that I myself never asked where the money I spent came from. I believe I am just as bad as you. Crofts Greatly reassured. Of course you are; and a very good thing too! What harm does it do after all? Rallying her jocularly So you don’t think me such a scoundrel now you come to think it over. Eh? Vivie I have shared profits with you: and I admitted you just now to the familiarity of knowing what I think of you. Crofts With serious friendliness. To be sure you did. You won’t find me a bad sort: I don’t go in for being superfine intellectually; but Ive plenty of honest human feeling; and the old Crofts breed comes out in a sort of instinctive hatred of anything low, in which I’m sure youll sympathize with me. Believe me, Miss Vivie, the world isn’t such a bad place as the croakers make out. As long as you don’t fly openly in the face of society, society doesn’t ask any inconvenient questions; and it makes precious short work of the cads who do. There are no secrets better kept than the secrets everybody guesses. In the class of people I can introduce you to, no lady or gentleman would so far forget themselves as to discuss my business affairs or your mothers. No man can offer you a safer position. Vivie Studying him curiously. I suppose you really think youre getting on famously with me. Crofts Well, I hope I may flatter myself that you think better of me than you did at first. Vivie Quietly. I hardly find you worth thinking about at all now. When I think of the society that tolerates you, and the laws that protect you! when I think of how helpless nine out of ten young girls would be in the hands of you and my mother! the unmentionable woman and her capitalist bully— Crofts Livid. Damn you! Vivie You need not. I feel among the damned already. She raises the latch of the gate to open it and go out. He follows her and puts his hand heavily on the top bar to prevent its opening. Crofts Panting with fury. Do you think I’ll put up with this from you, you young devil? Vivie Unmoved Be quiet. Some one will answer the bell. Without flinching a step she strikes the bell with the back of her hand. It clangs harshly; and he starts back involuntarily. Almost immediately Frank appears at the porch with his rifle. Frank With cheerful politeness. Will you have the rifle, Viv; or shall I operate? Vivie Frank: have you been listening? Frank Coming down into the garden. Only for the bell, I assure you; so that you shouldn’t have to wait. I think I shewed great insight into your character, Crofts. Crofts For two pins I’d take that gun from you and break it across your head. Frank Stalking him cautiously. Pray don’t. I’m ever so careless in handling firearms. Sure to be a fatal accident, with a reprimand from the coroner’s jury for my negligence. Vivie Put the rifle away, Frank: it’s quite unnecessary. Frank Quite right, Viv. Much more sportsmanlike to catch him in a trap. Crofts, understanding the insult, makes a threatening movement. Crofts: there are fifteen cartridges in the magazine here; and I am a dead shot at the present distance and at an object of your size. Crofts Oh, you needn’t be afraid. I’m not going to touch you. Frank Ever so magnanimous of you under the circumstances! Thank you. Crofts I’ll just tell you this before I go. It may interest you, since youre so fond of one another. Allow me, Mister Frank, to introduce you to your half-sister, the eldest daughter of the Reverend Samuel Gardner. Miss Vivie: you half-brother. Good morning! He goes out through the gate and along the road. Frank After a pause of stupefaction, raising the rifle Youll testify before the coroner that it’s an accident, Viv. He takes aim at the retreating figure of Crofts. Vivie seizes the muzzle and pulls it round against her breast. Vivie Fire now. You may. Frank Dropping his end of the rifle hastily Stop! take care. She lets it go. It falls on the turf. Oh, you’ve given your little boy such a turn. Suppose it had gone off! ugh! He sinks on the garden seat, overcome. Vivie Suppose it had: do you think it would not have been a relief to have some sharp physical pain tearing through me? Frank Coaxingly Take it ever so easy, dear Viv. Remember: even if the rifle scared that fellow into telling the truth for the first time in his life, that only makes us the babes in the woods in earnest. He holds out his arms to her. Come and be covered up with leaves again. Vivie With a cry of disgust. Ah, not that, not that. You make all my flesh creep. Frank Why, whats the matter? Vivie Goodbye. She makes for the gate. Frank Jumping up. Hallo! Stop! Viv! Viv! She turns in the gateway Where are you going to? Where shall we find you? Vivie At Honoria Fraser’s chambers, 67 Chancery Lane, for the rest of my life. She goes off quickly in the opposite direction to that taken by Crofts. Frank But I say—wait—dash it! He runs after her.

Act IV

Honoria Fraser’s chambers in Chancery Lane. An office at the top of New Stone Buildings, with a plate-glass window, distempered walls, electric light, and a patent stove. Saturday afternoon. The chimneys of Lincoln’s Inn and the western sky beyond are seen through the window. There is a double writing table in the middle of the room, with a cigar box, ash pans, and a portable electric reading lamp almost snowed up in heaps of papers and books. This table has knee holes and chairs right and left and is very untidy. The clerk’s desk, closed and tidy, with its high stool, is against the wall, near a door communicating with the inner rooms. In the opposite wall is the door leading to the public corridor. Its upper panel is of opaque glass, lettered in black on the outside, Fraser and Warren. A baize screen hides the corner between this door and the window. Frank, in a fashionable light-colored coaching suit, with his stick, gloves, and white hat in his hands, is pacing up and down in the office. Somebody tries the door with a key. Frank Calling. Come in. It’s not locked. Vivie comes in, in her hat and jacket. She stops and stares at him. Vivie Sternly. What are you doing here? Frank Waiting to see you. I’ve been here for hours. Is this the way you attend to your business? He puts his hat and stick on the table, and perches himself with a vault on the clerk’s stool, looking at her with every appearance of being in a specially restless, teasing, flippant mood. Vivie I’ve been away exactly twenty minutes for a cup of tea. She takes off her hat and jacket and hangs them behind the screen. How did you get in? Frank The staff had not left when I arrived. He’s gone to play cricket on Primrose Hill. Why don’t you employ a woman, and give your sex a chance? Vivie What have you come for? Frank Springing off the stool and coming close to her. Viv: lets go and enjoy the Saturday half-holiday somewhere, like the staff. What do you say to Richmond, and then a music hall, and a jolly supper? Vivie Can’t afford it. I shall put in another six hours work before I go to bed. Frank Can’t afford it, can’t we? Aha! Look here. He takes out a handful of sovereigns and makes them chink. Gold, Viv: gold! Vivie Where did you get it? Frank Gambling, Viv: gambling. Poker. Vivie Pah! It’s meaner than stealing it. No: I’m not coming. She sits down to work at the table, with her back to the glass door, and begins turning over the papers. Frank Remonstrating piteously. But, my dear Viv, I want to talk to you ever so seriously. Vivie Very well: sit down in Honoria’s chair and talk here. I like ten minutes chat after tea. He murmurs. No use groaning: I’m inexorable. He takes the opposite seat disconsolately. Pass that cigar box, will you? Frank Pushing the cigar box across. Nasty womanly habit. Nice men don’t do it any longer. Vivie Yes: they object to the smell in the office; and we’ve had to take to cigarets. See! She opens the box and takes out a cigaret, which she lights. She offers him one; but he shakes his head with a wry face. She settles herself comfortably in her chair, smoking. Go ahead. Frank Well, I want to know what you’ve done—what arrangements you’ve made. Vivie Everything was settled twenty minutes after I arrived here. Honoria has found the business too much for her this year; and she was on the point of sending for me and proposing a partnership when I walked in and told her I hadn’t a farthing in the world. So I installed myself and packed her off for a fortnight’s holiday. What happened at Haslemere when I left? Frank Nothing at all. I said youd gone to town on particular business. Vivie Well? Frank Well, either they were too flabbergasted to say anything, or else Crofts had prepared your mother. Anyhow, she didn’t say anything; and Crofts didn’t say anything; and Praddy only stared. After tea they got up and went; and I’ve not seen them since. Vivie Nodding placidly with one eye on a wreath of smoke. Thats all right. Frank Looking round disparagingly. Do you intend to stick in this confounded place? Vivie Blowing the wreath decisively away, and sitting straight up. Yes. These two days have given me back all my strength and self-possession. I will never take a holiday again as long as I live. Frank With a very wry face. Mps! You look quite happy. And as hard as nails. Vivie Grimly. Well for me that I am! Frank Rising Look here, Viv: we must have an explanation. We parted the other day under a complete misunderstanding. He sits on the table, close to her. Vivie Putting away the cigaret. Well: clear it up. Frank You remember what Crofts said. Vivie Yes. Frank That revelation was supposed to bring about a complete change in the nature of our feeling for one another. It placed us on the footing of brother and sister. Vivie Yes. Frank Have you ever had a brother? Vivie No. Frank Then you don’t know what being brother and sister feels like? Now I have lots of sisters; and the fraternal feeling is quite familiar to me. I assure you my feeling for you is not the least in the world like it. The girls will go their way; I will go mine; and we shan’t care if we never see one another again. Thats brother and sister. But as to you, I can’t be easy if I have to pass a week without seeing you. Thats not brother and sister. Its exactly what I felt an hour before Crofts made his revelation. In short, dear Viv, it’s love’s young dream. Vivie Bitingly. The same feeling, Frank, that brought your father to my mother’s feet. Is that it? Frank So revolted that he slips off the table for a moment. I very strongly object, Viv, to have my feelings compared to any which the Reverend Samuel is capable of harboring; and I object still more to a comparison of you to your mother. Resuming his perch Besides, I don’t believe the story. I have taxed my father with it, and obtained from him what I consider tantamount to a denial. Vivie What did he say? Frank He said he was sure there must be some mistake. Vivie Do you believe him? Frank I am prepared to take his word against Crofts’. Vivie Does it make any difference? I mean in your imagination or conscience; for of course it makes no real difference. Frank Shaking his head. None whatever to me. Vivie Nor to me. Frank Staring But this is ever so surprising! He goes back to his chair. I thought our whole relations were altered in your imagination and conscience, as you put it, the moment those words were out of that brute’s muzzle. Vivie No: it was not that. I didn’t believe him. I only wish I could. Frank Eh? Vivie I think brother and sister would be a very suitable relation for us. Frank You really mean that? Vivie Yes. It’s the only relation I care for, even if we could afford any other. I mean that. Frank Raising his eyebrows like one on whom a new light has dawned, and rising with quite an effusion of chivalrous sentiment. My dear Viv: why didn’t you say so before? I am ever so sorry for persecuting you. I understand, of course. Vivie Puzzled. Understand what? Frank Oh, I’m not a fool in the ordinary sense: only in the Scriptural sense of doing all the things the wise man declared to be folly, after trying them himself on the most extensive scale. I see I am no longer Vivvums’s little boy. Don’t be alarmed: I shall never call you Vivvums again—at least unless you get tired of your new little boy, whoever he may be. Vivie My new little boy! Frank With conviction. Must be a new little boy. Always happens that way. No other way, in fact. Vivie None that you know of, fortunately for you. Someone knocks at the door. Frank My curse upon yon caller, whoe’er he be! Vivie It’s Praed. He’s going to Italy and wants to say goodbye. I asked him to call this afternoon. Go and let him in. Frank We can continue our conversation after his departure for Italy. I’ll stay him out. He goes to the door and opens it. How are you, Praddy? Delighted to see you. Come in. Praed, dressed for travelling, comes in, in high spirits. Praed How do you do, Miss Warren? She presses his hand cordially, though a certain sentimentality in his high spirits jars upon her. I start in an hour from Holborn Viaduct. I wish I could persuade you to try Italy. Vivie What for? Praed Why, to saturate yourself with beauty and romance, of course. Vivie, with a shudder, turns her chair to the table, as if the work waiting for her there were a support to her. Praed sits opposite to her. Frank places a chair near Vivie, and drops lazily and carelessly into it, talking at her over his shoulder. Frank No use, Praddy. Viv is a little Philistine. She is indifferent tomy romance, and insensible to my beauty. Vivie Mr. Praed: once for all, there is no beauty and no romance in life for me. Life is what it is; and I am prepared to take it as it is. Praed Enthusiastically. You will not say that if you come with me to Verona and on to Venice. You will cry with delight at living in such a beautiful world. Frank This is most eloquent, Praddy. Keep it up. Praed Oh, I assure you I have cried—I shall cry again, I hope—at fifty! At your age, Miss Warren, you would not need to go so far as Verona. Your spirits would absolutely fly up at the mere sight of Ostend. You would be charmed with the gaiety, the vivacity, the happy air of Brussels. Vivie Springing up with an exclamation of loathing. Agh! Praed Rising. Whats the matter? Frank Rising. Hallo, Viv! Vivie To Praed, with deep reproach. Can you find no better example of your beauty and romance than Brussels to talk to me about? Praed Puzzled. Of course it’s very different from Verona. I don’t suggest for a moment that— Vivie Bitterly. Probably the beauty and romance come to much the same in both places. Praed Completely sobered and much concerned. My dear Miss Warren: I—looking enquiringly at Frank Is anything the matter? Frank She thinks your enthusiasm frivolous, Praddy. She’s had ever such a serious call. Vivie Sharply. Hold your tongue, Frank. Don’t be silly. Frank Sitting down. Do you call this good manners, Praed? Praed Anxious and considerate. Shall I take him away, Miss Warren? I feel sure we have disturbed you at your work. Vivie Sit down: I’m not ready to go back to work yet. Praed sits. You both think I have an attack of nerves. Not a bit of it. But there are two subjects I want dropped, if you don’t mind. One of them to Frank is love’s young dream in any shape or form: the other to Praed is the romance and beauty of life, especially Ostend and the gaiety of Brussels. You are welcome to any illusions you may have left on these subjects: I have none. If we three are to remain friends, I must be treated as a woman of business, permanently single to Frank and permanently unromantic to Praed. Frank I also shall remain permanently single until you change your mind. Praddy: change the subject. Be eloquent about something else. Praed Diffidently. I’m afraid theres nothing else in the world that Ican talk about. The Gospel of Art is the only one I can preach. I know Miss Warren is a great devotee of the Gospel of Getting On; but we can’t discuss that without hurting your feelings, Frank, since you are determined not to get on. Frank Oh, don’t mind my feelings. Give me some improving advice by all means: it does me ever so much good. Have another try to make a successful man of me, Viv. Come: lets have it all: energy, thrift, foresight, self-respect, character. Don’t you hate people who have no character, Viv? Vivie Wincing. Oh, stop, stop. Let us have no more of that horrible cant. Mr. Praed: if there are really only those two gospels in the world, we had better all kill ourselves; for the same taint is in both, through and through. Frank Looking critically at her. There is a touch of poetry about you today, Viv, which has hitherto been lacking. Praed Remonstrating. My dear Frank: aren’t you a little unsympathetic? Vivie Merciless to herself. No: it’s good for me. It keeps me from being sentimental. Frank Bantering her. Checks your strong natural propensity that way, don’t it? Vivie Almost hysterically. Oh yes: go on: don’t spare me. I was sentimental for one moment in my life—beautifully sentimental—by moonlight; and now— Frank Quickly. I say, Viv: take care. Don’t give yourself away. Vivie Oh, do you think Mr. Praed does not know all about my mother? Turning on Praed You had better have told me that morning, Mr. Praed. You are very old fashioned in your delicacies, after all. Praed Surely it is you who are a little old fashioned in your prejudices, Miss Warren. I feel bound to tell you, speaking as an artist, and believing that the most intimate human relationships are far beyond and above the scope of the law, that though I know that your mother is an unmarried woman, I do not respect her the less on that account. I respect her more. Frank Airily. Hear! hear! Vivie Staring at him. Is that all you know? Praed Certainly that is all. Vivie Then you neither of you know anything. Your guesses are innocence itself compared with the truth. Praed Rising, startled and indignant, and preserving his politeness with an effort. I hope not. More emphatically I hope not, Miss Warren. Frank Whistles. Whew! Vivie You are not making it easy for me to tell you, Mr. Praed. Praed His chivalry drooping before their conviction. If there is anything worse—that is, anything else—are you sure you are right to tell us, Miss Warren? Vivie I am sure that if I had the courage I should spend the rest of my life in telling everybody—stamping and branding it into them until they all felt their part in its abomination as I feel mine. There is nothing I despise more than the wicked convention that protects these things by forbidding a woman to mention them. And yet I can’t tell you. The two infamous words that describe what my mother is are ringing in my ears and struggling on my tongue; but I can’t utter them: the shame of them is too horrible for me. She buries her face in her hands. The two men, astonished, stare at one another and then at her. She raises her head again desperately and snatches a sheet of paper and a pen. Here: let me draft you a prospectus. Frank Oh, she’s mad. Do you hear, Viv? mad. Come! pull yourself together. Vivie You shall see. She writes. “Paid up capital: not less than forty thousand pounds standing in the name of Sir George Crofts, Baronet, the chief shareholder. Premises at Brussels, Ostend, Vienna, and Budapest. Managing director: Mrs. Warren”; and now don’t let us forget her qualifications: the two words. She writes the words and pushes the paper to them. There! Oh no: don’t read it: don’t! She snatches it back and tears it to pieces; then seizes her head in her hands and hides her face on the table. Frank, who has watched the writing over her shoulder, and opened his eyes very widely at it, takes a card from his pocket; scribbles the two words on it; and silently hands it to Praed, who reads it with amazement, and hides it hastily in his pocket. Frank Whispering tenderly. Viv, dear: thats all right. I read what you wrote: so did Praddy. We understand. And we remain, as this leaves us at present, yours ever so devotedly. Praed We do indeed, Miss Warren. I declare you are the most splendidly courageous woman I ever met. This sentimental compliment braces Vivie. She throws it away from her with an impatient shake, and forces herself to stand up, though not without some support from the table. Frank Don’t stir, Viv, if you don’t want to. Take it easy. Vivie Thank you. You an always depend on me for two things: not to cry and not to faint. She moves a few steps towards the door of the inner room, and stops close to Praed to say I shall need much more courage than that when I tell my mother that we have come to a parting of the ways. Now I must go into the next room for a moment to make myself neat again, if you don’t mind. Praed Shall we go away? Vivie No: I’ll be back presently. Only for a moment. She goes into the other room, Praed opening the door for her. Praed What an amazing revelation! I’m extremely disappointed in Crofts: I am indeed. Frank I’m not in the least. I feel he’s perfectly accounted for at last. But what a facer for me, Praddy! I can’t marry her now. Praed Sternly Frank! The two look at one another, Frank unruffled, Praed deeply indignant. Let me tell you, Gardner, that if you desert her now you will behave very despicably. Frank Good old Praddy! Ever chivalrous! But you mistake: it’s not the moral aspect of the case: it’s the money aspect. I really can’t bring myself to touch the old woman’s money now. Praed And was that what you were going to marry on? Frank What else? I havn’t any money, nor the smallest turn for making it. If I married Viv now she would have to support me; and I should cost her more than I am worth. Praed But surely a clever bright fellow like you can make something by your own brains. Frank Oh yes, a little. He takes out his money again. I made all that yesterday in an hour and a half. But I made it in a highly speculative business. No, dear Praddy: even if Bessie and Georgina marry millionaires and the governor dies after cutting them off with a shilling, I shall have only four hundred a year. And he won’t die until he’s three score and ten: he hasn’t originality enough. I shall be on short allowance for the next twenty years. No short allowance for Viv, if I can help it. I withdraw gracefully and leave the field to the gilded youth of England. So that settled. I shan’t worry her about it: I’ll just send her a little note after we’re gone. She’ll understand. Praed Grasping his hand. Good fellow, Frank! I heartily beg your pardon. But must you never see her again? Frank Never see her again! Hang it all, be reasonable. I shall come along as often as possible, and be her brother. I can not understand the absurd consequences you romantic people expect from the most ordinary transactions. A knock at the door. I wonder who this is. Would you mind opening the door? If it’s a client it will look more respectable than if I appeared. Praed Certainly. He goes to the door and opens it. Frank sits down in Vivie’s chair to scribble a note. My dear Kitty: come in: come in. Mrs. Warren comes in, looking apprehensively around for Vivie. She has done her best to make herself matronly and dignified. The brilliant hat is replaced by a sober bonnet, and the gay blouse covered by a costly black silk mantle. She is pitiably anxious and ill at ease: evidently panic-stricken. Mrs. Warren To Frank. What! Youre here, are you? Frank Turning in his chair from his writing, but not rising. Here, and charmed to see you. You come like a breath of spring. Mrs. Warren Oh, get out with your nonsense. In a low voice Where’s Vivie? Frank points expressively to the door of the inner room, but says nothing. Mrs. Warren Sitting down suddenly and almost beginning to cry. Praddy: won’t she see me, don’t you think? Praed My dear Kitty: don’t distress yourself. Why should she not? Mrs. Warren Oh, you never can see why not: youre too innocent. Mr. Frank: did she say anything to you? Frank Folding his note. She must see you, if very expressively you wait til she comes in. Mrs. Warren Frightened. Why shouldn’t I wait? Frank looks quizzically at her; puts his note carefully on the ink-bottle, so that Vivie cannot fail to find it when next she dips her pen; then rises and devotes his attention entirely to her. Frank My dear Mrs. Warren: suppose you were a sparrow—ever so tiny and pretty a sparrow hopping in the roadway—and you saw a steam roller coming in your direction, would you wait for it? Mrs. Warren Oh, don’t bother me with your sparrows. What did she run away from Haslemere like that for? Frank I’m afraid she’ll tell you if you rashly await her return. Mrs. Warren Do you want me to go away? Frank No: I always want you to stay. But I advise you to go away. Mrs. Warren What! And never see her again! Frank Precisely. Mrs. Warren Crying again Praddy: don’t let him be cruel to me. She hastily checks her tears and wipes her eyes. She’ll be so angry if she sees I’ve been crying. Frank With a touch of real compassion in his airy tenderness. You know that Praddy is the soul of kindness, Mrs. Warren. Praddy: what do you say? Go or stay? Praed To Mrs. Warren I really should be very sorry to cause you unnecessary pain; but I think perhaps you had better not wait. The fact is—Vivie is heard at the inner door. Frank Sh! Too late. She’s coming. Mrs. Warren Don’t tell her I was crying. Vivie comes in. She stops gravely on seeing Mrs. Warren, who greets her with hysterical cheerfulness. Well, dearie. So here you are at last. Vivie I am glad you have come: I want to speak to you. You said you were going, Frank, I think. Frank Yes. Will you come with me, Mrs. Warren? What do you say to a trip to Richmond, and the theatre in the evening? There is safety in Richmond. No steam roller there. Vivie Nonsense, Frank. My mother will stay here. Mrs. Warren Scared. I don’t know: perhaps I’d better go. We’re disturbing you at your work. Vivie With quiet decision Mr. Praed: please take Frank away. Sit down, mother. Mrs. Warren obeys helplessly. Praed Come, Frank. Goodbye, Miss Vivie. Vivie Shaking hands. Goodbye. A pleasant trip. Praed Thank you: thank you. I hope so. Frank To Mrs. Warren. Goodbye: youd ever so much better have taken my advice. He shakes hands with her. Then airily to Vivie Byebye, Viv. Vivie Goodbye. He goes out gaily without shaking hands with her. Praed Sadly. Goodbye, Kitty. Mrs. Warren Snivelling.—oobye! Praed goes. Vivie, composed and extremely grave, sits down in Honoria’s chair, and waits for her mother to speak. Mrs. Warren, dreading a pause, loses no time in beginning. Mrs. Warren Well, Vivie, what did you go away like that for without saying a word to me! How could you do such a thing! And what have you done to poor George? I wanted him to come with me; but he shuffled out of it. I could see that he was quite afraid of you. Only fancy: he wanted me not to come. As if trembling I should be afraid of you, dearie. Vivie’s gravity deepens. But of course I told him it was all settled and comfortable between us, and that we were on the best of terms. She breaks down. Vivie: whats the meaning of this? She produces a commercial envelope, and fumbles at the enclosure with trembling fingers. I got it from the bank this morning. Vivie It is my month’s allowance. They sent it to me as usual the other day. I simply sent it back to be placed to your credit, and asked them to send you the lodgment receipt. In future I shall support myself. Mrs. Warren Not daring to understand. Wasn’t it enough? Why didn’t you tell me? With a cunning gleam in her eye I’ll double it: I was intending to double it. Only let me know how much you want. Vivie You know very well that that has nothing to do with it. From this time I go my own way in my own business and among my own friends. And you will go yours. She rises. Goodbye. Mrs. Warren Rising, appalled. Goodbye? Vivie Yes: goodbye. Come: don’t let us make a useless scene: you understand perfectly well. Sir George Crofts has told me the whole business. Mrs. Warren Angrily Silly old—She swallows an epithet, and then turns white at the narrowness of her escape from uttering it. Vivie Just so. Mrs. Warren He ought to have his tongue cut out. But I thought it was ended: you said you didn’t mind. Vivie Steadfastly. Excuse me: I do mind. Mrs. Warren But I explained— Vivie You explained how it came about. You did not tell me that it is still going on She sits. Mrs. Warren, silenced for a moment, looks forlornly at Vivie, who waits, secretly hoping that the combat is over. But the cunning expression comes back into Mrs. Warren’s face; and she bends across the table, sly and urgent, half whispering. Mrs. Warren Vivie: do you know how rich I am? Vivie I have no doubt you are very rich. Mrs. Warren But you don’t know all that that means; youre too young. It means a new dress every day; it means theatres and balls every night; it means having the pick of all the gentlemen in Europe at your feet; it means a lovely house and plenty of servants; it means the choicest of eating and drinking; it means everything you like, everything you want, everything you can think of. And what are you here? A mere drudge, toiling and moiling early and late for your bare living and two cheap dresses a year. Think over it. Soothingly Youre shocked, I know. I can enter into your feelings; and I think they do you credit; but trust me, nobody will blame you: you may take my word for that. I know what young girls are; and I know youll think better of it when you’ve turned it over in your mind. Vivie So that’s how it is done, is it? You must have said all that to many a woman, to have it so pat. Mrs. Warren Passionately. What harm am I asking you to do? Vivie turns away contemptuously. Mrs. Warren continues desperately Vivie: listen to me: you don’t understand: you were taught wrong on purpose: you don’t know what the world is really like. Vivie Arrested. Taught wrong on purpose! What do you mean? Mrs. Warren I mean that youre throwing away all your chances for nothing. You think that people are what they pretend to be: that the way you were taught at school and college to think right and proper is the way things really are. But it’s not: it’s all only a pretence, to keep the cowardly slavish common run of people quiet. Do you want to find that out, like other women, at forty, when you’ve thrown yourself away and lost your chances; or won’t you take it in good time now from your own mother, that loves you and swears to you that it’s truth: gospel truth? Urgently Vivie: the big people, the clever people, the managing people, all know it. They do as I do, and think what I think. I know plenty of them. I know them to speak to, to introduce you to, to make friends of for you. I don’t mean anything wrong: thats what you don’t understand: your head is full of ignorant ideas about me. What do the people that taught you know about life or about people like me? When did they ever meet me, or speak to me, or let anyone tell them about me? the fools! Would they ever have done anything for you if I hadn’t paid them? Havn’t I told you that I want you to be respectable? Havn’t I brought you up to be respectable? And how can you keep it up without my money and my influence and Lizzie’s friends? Can’t you see that youre cutting your own throat as well as breaking my heart in turning your back on me? Vivie I recognize the Crofts philosophy of life, mother. I heard it all from him that day at the Gardners’. Mrs. Warren You think I want to force that played-out old sot on you! I don’t, Vivie: on my oath I don’t. Vivie It would not matter if you did: you would not succeed. Mrs. Warren winces, deeply hurt by the implied indifference towards her affectionate intention. Vivie, neither understanding this nor concerning herself about it, goes on calmly Mother: you don’t at all know the sort of person I am. I don’t object to Crofts more than to any other coarsely built man of his class. To tell you the truth, I rather admire him for being strongminded enough to enjoy himself in his own way and make plenty of money instead of living the usual shooting, hunting, dining-out, tailoring, loafing life of his set merely because all the rest do it. And I’m perfectly aware that if I’d been in the same circumstances as my aunt Liz, I’d have done exactly what she did. I don’t think I’m more prejudiced or straitlaced than you: I think I’m less. I’m certain I’m less sentimental. I know very well that fashionable morality is all a pretence, and that if I took your money and devoted the rest of my life to spending it fashionably, I might be as worthless and vicious as the silliest woman could possibly be without having a word said to me about it. But I don’t want to be worthless. I shouldn’t enjoy trotting about the park to advertize my dressmaker and carriage builder, or being bored at the opera to shew off a shopwindowful of diamonds. Mrs. Warren Bewildered. But— Vivie Wait a moment: I’ve not done. Tell me why you continue your business now that you are independent of it. Your sister, you told me, has left all that behind her. Why don’t you do the same? Mrs. Warren Oh, it’s all very easy for Liz: she likes good society, and has the air of being a lady. Imagine me in a cathedral town! Why, the very rooks in the trees would find me out even if I could stand the dulness of it. I must have work and excitement, or I should go melancholy mad. And what else is there for me to do? The life suits me: I’m fit for it and not for anything else. If I didn’t do it somebody else would; so I don’t do any real harm by it. And then it brings in money; and I like making money. No: it’s no use: I can’t give it up—not for anybody. But what need you know about it? I’ll never mention it. I’ll keep Crofts away. I’ll not trouble you much: you see I have to be constantly running about from one place to another. Youll be quit of me altogether when I die. Vivie No: I am my mother’s daughter. I am like you: I must have work, and must make more money than I spend. But my work is not your work, and my way is not your way. We must part. It will not make much difference to us: instead of meeting one another for perhaps a few months in twenty years, we shall never meet: thats all. Mrs. Warren Her voice stifled in tears. Vivie: I meant to have been more with you: I did indeed. Vivie It’s no use, mother: I am not to be changed by a few cheap tears and entreaties any more than you are, I daresay. Mrs. Warren Wildly. Oh, you call a mother’s tears cheap. Vivie They cost you nothing; and you ask me to give you the peace and quietness of my whole life in exchange for them. What use would my company be to you if you could get it? What have we two in common that could make either of us happy together? Mrs. Warren Lapsing recklessly into her dialect. We’re mother and daughter. I want my daughter. I’ve a right to you. Who is to care for me when I’m old? Plenty of girls have taken to me like daughters and cried at leaving me; but I let them all go because I had you to look forward to. I kept myself lonely for you. You’ve no right to turn on me now and refuse to do your duty as a daughter. Vivie Jarred and antagonized by the echo of the slums in her mother’s voice. My duty as a daughter! I thought we should come to that presently. Now once for all, mother, you want a daughter and Frank wants a wife. I don’t want a mother; and I don’t want a husband. I have spared neither Frank nor myself in sending him about his business. Do you think I will spare you? Mrs. Warren Violently. Oh, I know the sort you are: no mercy for yourself or anyone else. I know. My experience has done that for me anyhow: I can tell the pious, canting, hard, selfish woman when I meet her. Well, keep yourself to yourself: I don’t want you. But listen to this. Do you know what I would do with you if you were a baby again? aye, as sure as there’s a Heaven above us. Vivie Strangle me, perhaps. Mrs. Warren No: I’d bring you up to be a real daughter to me, and not what you are now, with your pride and your prejudices and the college education you stole from me: yes, stole: deny it if you can: what was it but stealing? I’d bring you up in my own house, I would. Vivie Quietly. In one of your own houses. Mrs. Warren Screaming. Listen to her! listen to how she spits on her mother’s grey hairs! Oh, may you live to have your own daughter tear and trample on you as you have trampled on me. And you will: you will. No woman ever had luck with a mother’s curse on her. Vivie I wish you wouldn’t rant, mother. It only hardens me. Come: I suppose I am the only young woman you ever had in your power that you did good to. Don’t spoil it all now. Mrs. Warren Yes, Heaven forgive me, it’s true; and you are the only one that ever turned on me. Oh, the injustice of it! the injustice! the injustice! I always wanted to be a good woman. I tried honest work; and I was slave-driven until I cursed the day I ever heard of honest work. I was a good mother; and because I made my daughter a good woman she turns me out as if I were a leper. Oh, if I only had my life to live over again! I’d talk to that lying clergyman in the school. From this time forth, so help me Heaven in my last hour, I’ll do wrong and nothing but wrong. And I’ll prosper on it. Vivie Yes: it’s better to choose your line and go through with it. If I had been you, mother, I might have done as you did; but I should not have lived one life and believed in another. You are a conventional woman at heart. That is why I am bidding you goodbye now. I am right, am I not? Mrs. Warren Taken aback. Right to throw away all my money! Vivie No: right to get rid of you? I should be a fool not to. Isn’t that so? Mrs. Warren Sulkily Oh well, yes, if you come to that, I suppose you are. But Lord help the world if everybody took to doing the right thing! And now I’d better go than stay where I’m not wanted. She turns to the door. Vivie Kindly. Won’t you shake hands? Mrs. Warren After looking at her fiercely for a moment with a savage impulse to strike her. No, thank you. Goodbye. Vivie Matter-of-factly Goodbye. Mrs. Warren goes out, slamming the door behind her. The strain on Vivie’s face relaxes; her grave expression breaks up into one of joyous content; her breath goes out in a half sob, half laugh of intense relief. She goes buoyantly to her place at the writing table; pushes the electric lamp out of the way; pulls over a great sheaf of papers; and is in the act of dipping her pen in the ink when she finds Frank’s note. She opens it unconcernedly and reads it quickly, giving a little laugh at some quaint turn of expression in it. And goodbye, Frank. She tears the note up and tosses the pieces into the wastepaper basket without a second thought. Then she goes at her work with a plunge, and soon becomes absorbed in its figures.

Act IV

Honoria Fraser’s chambers in Chancery Lane. An office at the top of New Stone Buildings, with a plate-glass window, distempered walls, electric light, and a patent stove. Saturday afternoon. The chimneys of Lincoln’s Inn and the western sky beyond are seen through the window. There is a double writing table in the middle of the room, with a cigar box, ash pans, and a portable electric reading lamp almost snowed up in heaps of papers and books. This table has knee holes and chairs right and left and is very untidy. The clerk’s desk, closed and tidy, with its high stool, is against the wall, near a door communicating with the inner rooms. In the opposite wall is the door leading to the public corridor. Its upper panel is of opaque glass, lettered in black on the outside, “Fraser and Warren.” A baize screen hides the corner between this door and the window.

Frank, in a fashionable light-colored coaching suit, with his stick, gloves, and white hat in his hands, is pacing up and down in the office. Somebody tries the door with a key.
Frank | Calling. Come in. It’s not locked.
Vivie comes in, in her hat and jacket. She stops and stares at him.
Vivie | Sternly. What are you doing here?
Frank | Waiting to see you. I’ve been here for hours. Is this the way you attend to your business? He puts his hat and stick on the table, and perches himself with a vault on the clerk’s stool, looking at her with every appearance of being in a specially restless, teasing, flippant mood.
Vivie | I’ve been away exactly twenty minutes for a cup of tea. She takes off her hat and jacket and hangs them behind the screen. How did you get in?
Frank | The staff had not left when I arrived. He’s gone to play football on Primrose Hill. Why don’t you employ a woman, and give your sex a chance?
Vivie | What have you come for?
Frank | Springing off the stool and coming close to her. Viv: let’s go and enjoy the Saturday half-holiday somewhere, like the staff. What do you say to Richmond, and then a music hall, and a jolly supper?
Vivie | Can’t afford it. I shall put in another six hours’ work before I go to bed.
Frank | Can’t afford it, can’t we? Aha! Look here. He takes out a handful of sovereigns and makes them chink. Gold, Viv, gold!
Vivie | Where did you get it?
Frank | Gambling, Viv: gambling. Poker.
Vivie | Pah! It’s meaner than stealing it. No: I’m not coming. She sits down to work at the table, with her back to the glass door, and begins turning over the papers.
Frank | Remonstrating piteously. But, my dear Viv, I want to talk to you ever so seriously.
Vivie | Very well: sit down in Honoria’s chair and talk here. I like ten minutes’ chat after tea. He murmurs. No use groaning: I’m inexorable. He takes the opposite seat disconsolately. Pass that cigar box, will you?
Frank | Pushing the cigar box across. Nasty womanly habit. Nice men don’t do it any longer.
Vivie | Yes: they object to the smell in the office; and we’ve had to take to cigarettes. See! She opens the box and takes out a cigarette, which she lights. She offers him one; but he shakes his head with a wry face. She settles herself comfortably in her chair, smoking. Go ahead.
Frank | Well, I want to know what you’ve done—what arrangements you’ve made.
Vivie | Everything was settled twenty minutes after I arrived here. Honoria has found the business too much for her this year; and she was on the point of sending for me and proposing a partnership when I walked in and told her I hadn’t a farthing in the world. So I installed myself and packed her off for a fortnight’s holiday. What happened at Haslemere when I left?
Frank | Nothing at all. I said you’d gone to town on particular business.
Vivie | Well?
Frank | Well, either they were too flabbergasted to say anything, or else Crofts had prepared your mother. Anyhow, she didn’t say anything; and Crofts didn’t say anything; and Praddy only stared. After tea they got up and went; and I’ve not seen them since.
Vivie | Nodding placidly with one eye on a wreath of smoke. That’s all right.
Frank | Looking round disparagingly. Do you intend to stick in this confounded place?
Vivie | Blowing the wreath decisively away, and sitting straight up. Yes. These two days have given me back all my strength and self-possession. I will never take a holiday again as long as I live.
Frank | With a very wry face. Mps! You look quite happy—and as hard as nails.
Vivie | Grimly. Well for me that I am!
Frank | Rising. Look here, Viv: we must have an explanation. We parted the other day under a complete misunderstanding.
Vivie | Putting away the cigarette. Well: clear it up.
Frank | You remember what Crofts said?
Vivie | Yes.
Frank | That revelation was supposed to bring about a complete change in the nature of our feeling for one another. It placed us on the footing of brother and sister.
Vivie | Yes.
Frank | Have you ever had a brother?
Vivie | No.
Frank | Then you don’t know what being brother and sister feels like? Now I have lots of sisters: Jessie and Georgina and the rest. The fraternal feeling is quite familiar to me; and I assure you my feeling for you is not the least in the world like it. The girls will go their way; I will go mine; and we shan’t care if we never see one another again. That’s brother and sister. But as to you, I can’t be easy if I have to pass a week without seeing you. That’s not brother and sister. It’s exactly what I felt an hour before Crofts made his revelation. In short, dear Viv, it’s love’s young dream.
Vivie | Bitingly. The same feeling, Frank, that brought your father to my mother’s feet. Is that it?
Frank | Revolted. I very strongly object, Viv, to have my feelings compared to any which the Reverend Samuel is capable of harboring; and I object still more to a comparison of you to your mother. Resuming his perch. Besides, I don’t believe the story. I have taxed my father with it, and obtained from him what I consider tantamount to a denial.
Vivie | What did he say?
Frank | He said he was sure there must be some mistake.
Vivie | Do you believe him?
Frank | I am prepared to take his word against Crofts’.
Vivie | Does it make any difference? I mean in your imagination or conscience; for of course it makes no real difference.
Frank | Shaking his head. None whatever to me.
Vivie | Nor to me.
Frank | Staring. But this is ever so surprising! He goes back to his chair. I thought our whole relations were altered in your imagination and conscience, as you put it, the moment those words were out of that brute’s muzzle.
Vivie | No: it was not that. I didn’t believe him. I only wish I could.
Frank | Eh?
Vivie | I think brother and sister would be a very suitable relation for us.
Frank | You really mean that?
Vivie | Yes. It’s the only relation I care for, even if we could afford any other. I mean that.
Frank | Raising his eyebrows like one on whom a new light has dawned, and rising with quite an effusion of chivalrous sentiment. My dear Viv: why didn’t you say so before? I am ever so sorry for persecuting you. I understand, of course.
Vivie | Puzzled. Understand what?
Frank | Oh, I’m not a fool in the ordinary sense—only in the Scriptural sense of doing all the things the wise man declared to be folly, after trying them himself on the most extensive scale. I see I am no longer Vivvums’ little boy. Don’t be alarmed: I shall never call you Vivvums again—at least unless you get tired of your new little boy, whoever he may be.
Vivie | My new little boy!
Frank | With conviction. Must be a new little boy. Always happens that way. No other way, in fact.
Vivie | None that you know of, fortunately for you.
Someone knocks at the door.
Frank | My curse upon yon caller, whoe’er he be!
Vivie | It’s Praed. He’s going to Italy and wants to say goodbye. I asked him to call this afternoon. Go and let him in.
Frank | We can continue our conversation after his departure for Italy. I’ll stay him out. He goes to the door and opens it. How are you, Praddy? Delighted to see you. Come in. Praed, dressed for travelling, comes in, in high spirits.
Praed | How do you do, Miss Warren. She presses his hand cordially, though a certain sentimentality in his high spirits jars upon her. I start in an hour from Holborn Viaduct. I wish I could persuade you to try Italy.
Vivie | What for?
Praed | Why, to saturate yourself with beauty and romance, of course. Vivie, with a shudder, turns her chair to the table, as if the work waiting for her there were a consolation and support to her. Praed sits opposite to her. Frank places a chair just behind Vivie, and drops lazily and carelessly into it, talking at her over his shoulder.
Frank | No use, Praddy. Viv is a little Philistine. She is indifferent to my romance, and insensible to my beauty.
Vivie | Mr. Praed: once for all, there is no beauty and no romance in life for me. Life is what it is; and I am prepared to take it as it is.
Praed | Enthusiastically. You will not say that if you come to Verona and on to Venice. You will cry with delight at living in such a beautiful world.
Frank | This is most eloquent, Praddy. Keep it up.
Praed | Oh, I assure you I have cried—I shall cry again, I hope—at fifty! At your age, Miss Warren, you would not need to go so far as Verona. Your spirits would absolutely fly up at the mere sight of Ostend. You would be charmed with the gaiety, the vivacity, the happy air of Brussels. Vivie recoils. What’s the matter?
Frank | Hallo, Viv!
Vivie | To Praed with deep reproach. Can you find no better example of your beauty and romance than Brussels to talk to me about?
Praed | Puzzled. Of course it’s very different from Verona. I don’t suggest for a moment that—
Vivie | Bitterly. Probably the beauty and romance come to much the same in both places.
Praed | Completely sobered and much concerned. My dear Miss Warren: I—Looking enquiringly at Frank. Is anything the matter?
Frank | She thinks your enthusiasm frivolous, Praddy. She’s had ever such a serious call.
Vivie | Sharply. Hold your tongue, Frank. Don’t be silly.
Frank | Calmly. Do you call this good manners, Praed?
Praed | Anxious and considerate. Shall I take him away, Miss Warren? I feel sure we have disturbed you at your work. He is about to rise.
Vivie | Sit down: I’m not ready to go back to work yet. You both think I have an attack of nerves. Not a bit of it. But there are two subjects I want dropped, if you don’t mind. One of them to Frank is love’s young dream in any shape or form: the other to Praed is the romance and beauty of life, especially as exemplified by the gaiety of Brussels. You are welcome to any illusions you may have left on these subjects: I have none. If we three are to remain friends, I must be treated as a woman of business, permanently single to Frank and permanently unromantic to Praed.
Frank | I also shall remain permanently single until you change your mind. Praddy: change the subject. Be eloquent about something else.
Praed | Diffidently. I’m afraid there’s nothing else in the world that I can talk about. The Gospel of Art is the only one I can preach. I know Miss Warren is a great devotee of the Gospel of Getting On; but we can’t discuss that without hurting your feelings, Frank, since you are determined not to get on.
Frank | Oh, don’t mind my feelings. Give me some improving advice by all means: it does me ever so much good. Have another try to make a successful man of me, Viv. Come: lets have it all: energy, thrift, foresight, self-respect, character. Don’t you hate people who have no character, Viv?
Vivie | Wincing. Oh, stop: stop: let us have no more of that horrible cant. Mr. Praed: if there are really only those two gospels in the world, we had better all kill ourselves; for the same taint is in both, through and through.
Frank | Looking critically at her. There is a touch of poetry about you today, Viv, which has hitherto been lacking.
Praed | Remonstrating. My dear Frank: aren’t you a little unsympathetic?
Vivie | Merciless to herself. No: it’s good for me. It keeps me from being sentimental.
Frank | Bantering her. Checks your strong natural propensity that way, don’t it?
Vivie | Almost hysterically. Oh yes: go on: don’t spare me. I was sentimental for one moment in my life—beautifully sentimental—by moonlight; and now—
Frank | Quickly. I say, Viv: take care. Don’t give yourself away.
Vivie | Oh, do you think Mr. Praed does not know all about my mother? Turning on Praed. You had better have told me that morning, Mr. Praed. You are very old fashioned in your delicacies, after all.
Praed | Surely it is you who are a little old fashioned in your prejudices, Miss Warren. I feel bound to tell you, speaking as an artist, and believing that the most intimate human relationships are far beyond and above the scope of the law, that though I know that your mother is an unmarried woman, I do not respect her the less on that account. I respect her more.
Frank | Airily. Hear, hear!
Vivie | Staring at him. Is that all you know?
Praed | Certainly that is all.
Vivie | Then you neither of you know anything. Your guesses are innocence itself compared with the truth.
Praed | Startled and indignant, preserving his politeness with an effort. I hope not. More emphatically. I hope not, Miss Warren. Frank’s face shows that he does not share Praed’s incredulity. Vivie utters an exclamation of impatience. Praed’s chivalry droops before their conviction. He adds, slowly: If there is anything worse—that is, anything else—are you sure you are right to tell us, Miss Warren?
Vivie | I am sure that if I had the courage I should spend the rest of my life in telling it to everybody—in stamping and branding it into them until they all felt their share in its shame and horror as I feel mine. There is nothing I despise more than the wicked convention that protects these things by forbidding a woman to mention them. And yet I can’t tell you. The two infamous words that describe what my mother is are ringing in my ears and struggling on my tongue; but I can’t utter them: the shame of them is too horrible for me. She buries her face in her hands. The two men, astonished, stare at one another and then at her. She raises her head again desperately and snatches a sheet of paper and a pen. Here: let me draft you a prospectus.
Frank | Oh, she’s mad. Do you hear, Viv? mad. Come: pull yourself together.
Vivie | You shall see. She writes. “Paid up capital: not less than forty thousand pounds standing in the name of Sir George Crofts, Baronet, the chief shareholder.” What comes next?—I forget. Oh, yes: “Premises at Brussels, Berlin, Vienna, and Budapest. Managing director: Mrs. Warren;” and now don’t let us forget her qualifications: the two words. There! She pushes the paper to them. Oh, no: don’t read it: don’t! She snatches it back and tears it to pieces; then seizes her head in her hands and hides her face on the table. Frank, who has watched the writing over her shoulder, and opened his eyes very widely at it, takes a card from his pocket; scribbles a couple of words; and silently hands it to Praed, who looks at it with amazement. Frank then remorsefully stoops over Vivie.
Frank | Whispering tenderly. Viv, dear: that’s all right. I read what you wrote: so did Praddy. We understand. And we remain, as this leaves us at present, yours ever so devotedly. Vivie slowly raises her head.
Praed | We do indeed, Miss Warren. I declare you are the most splendidly courageous woman I ever met.
This sentimental compliment braces Vivie. She throws it away from her with an impatient shake, and forces herself to stand up, though not without some support from the table.
Frank | Don’t stir, Viv, if you don’t want to. Take it easy.
Vivie | Thank you. You can always depend on me for two things, not to cry and not to faint. She moves a few steps towards the door of the inner room, and stops close to Praed to say: I shall need much more courage than that when I tell my mother that we have come to the parting of the ways. Now I must go into the next room for a moment to make myself neat again, if you don’t mind.
Praed | Shall we go away?
Vivie | No: I’ll be back presently. Only for a moment. She goes into the other room, Praed opening the door for her.
Praed | What an amazing revelation! I’m extremely disappointed in Crofts: I am indeed.
Frank | I’m not in the least. I feel he’s perfectly accounted for at last. But what a facer for me, Praddy! I can’t marry her now.
Praed | Sternly. Frank! The two look at one another, Frank unruffled, Praed deeply indignant. Let me tell you, Gardner, that if you desert her now you will behave very despicably.
Frank | Good old Praddy! Ever chivalrous! But you mistake: it’s not the moral aspect of the case: it’s the money aspect. I really can’t bring myself to touch the old woman’s money now?
Praed | And was that what you were going to marry on?
Frank | What else? I haven’t any money, nor the smallest turn for making it. If I married Viv now she would have to support me; and I should cost her more than I am worth.
Praed | But surely a clever bright fellow like you can make something by your own brains.
Frank | Oh, yes, a little. He takes out his money again. I made all that yesterday—in an hour and a half. But I made it in a highly speculative business. No, dear Praddy: even if Jessie and Georgina marry millionaires and the governor dies after cutting them off with a shilling, I shall have only four hundred a year. And he won’t die until he’s three score and ten: he hasn’t originality enough. I shall be on short allowance for the next twenty years. No short allowance for Viv, if I can help it. I withdraw gracefully and leave the field to the gilded youth of England. So that’s settled. I shan’t worry her about it: I’ll just send her a little note after we’re gone. She’ll understand.
Praed | Grasping his hand. Good fellow, Frank! I heartily beg your pardon. But must you never see her again?
Frank | Never see her again! Hang it all, be reasonable. I shall come along as often as possible, and be her brother. I can not understand the absurd consequences you romantic people expect from the most ordinary transactions. A knock at the door. I wonder who this is. Would you mind opening the door? If it’s a client it will look more respectable than if I appeared.
Praed | Certainly. He goes to the door and opens it. Frank sits down in Vivie’s chair to scribble a note. My dear Kitty: come in, come in.
Mrs. Warren comes in, looking apprehensively around for Vivie. She has done her best to make herself matronly and dignified. The brilliant hat is replaced by a sober bonnet, and the gay blouse covered by a costly black silk mantle. She is pitiably anxious and ill at ease—evidently panic-stricken.
Mrs. Warren | To Frank. What! You’re here, are you?
Frank | Turning in his chair from his writing, but not rising. Here, and charmed to see you. You come like a breath of spring.
Mrs. Warren | Oh, get out with your nonsense. In a low voice. Where’s Vivie?
Frank points expressively to the door of the inner room, but says nothing.
Mrs. Warren | Sitting down suddenly and almost beginning to cry. Praddy: won’t she see me, don’t you think?
Praed | My dear Kitty: don’t distress yourself. Why should she not?
Mrs. Warren | Oh, you never can see why not: you’re too innocent. Mr. Frank: did she say anything to you?
Frank | Folding his note. She must see you, if very expressively. you wait till she comes in.
Mrs. Warren | Frightened. Why shouldn’t I wait?
Frank looks quizzically at her; puts his note carefully on the ink-bottle, so that Vivie cannot fail to find it when next she dips her pen; then rises and devotes his attention entirely to her.
Frank | My dear Mrs. Warren: suppose you were a sparrow—ever so tiny and pretty a sparrow hopping in the roadway—and you saw a steam roller coming in your direction, would you wait for it?
Mrs. Warren | Oh, don’t bother me with your sparrows. What did she run away from Haslemere like that for?
Frank | I’m afraid she’ll tell you if you wait until she comes back.
Mrs. Warren | Do you want me to go away?
Frank | No. I always want you to stay. But I advise you to go away.
Mrs. Warren | What! And never see her again!
Frank | Precisely.
Mrs. Warren | Crying again. Praddy: don’t let him be cruel to me. She hastily checks her tears and wipes her eyes. She’ll be so angry if she sees I’ve been crying.
Frank | With a touch of real compassion in his airy tenderness. You know that Praddy is the soul of kindness, Mrs. Warren. Praddy: what do you say? Go or stay?
Praed | To Mrs. Warren. I really should be very sorry to cause you unnecessary pain; but I think perhaps you had better not wait. The fact is—Vivie is heard at the inner door.
Frank | Sh! Too late. She’s coming.
Mrs. Warren | Don’t tell her I was crying. Vivie comes in. She stops gravely on seeing Mrs. Warren, who greets her with hysterical cheerfulness. Well, dearie. So here you are at last.
Vivie | I am glad you have come: I want to speak to you. You said you were going, Frank, I think.
Frank | Yes. Will you come with me, Mrs. Warren? What do you say to a trip to Richmond, and the theatre in the evening? There is safety in Richmond. No steam roller there.
Vivie | Nonsense, Frank. My mother will stay here.
Mrs. Warren | Scared. I don’t know: perhaps I’d better go. We’re disturbing you at your work.
Vivie | With quiet decision. Mr. Praed: please take Frank away. Sit down, mother. Mrs. Warren obeys helplessly.
Praed | Come, Frank. Goodbye, Miss Vivie.
Vivie | Shaking hands. Goodbye. A pleasant trip.
Praed | Thank you: thank you. I hope so.
Frank | To Mrs. Warren. Goodbye: you’d ever so much better have taken my advice. He shakes hands with her. Then airily to Vivie. Bye-bye, Viv.
Vivie | Goodbye. He goes out gaily without shaking hands with her. Praed follows. Vivie, composed and extremely grave, sits down in Honoria’s chair, and waits for her mother to speak. Mrs. Warren, dreading a pause, loses no time in beginning.
Mrs. Warren | Well, Vivie, what did you go away like that for without saying a word to me? How could you do such a thing! And what have you done to poor George? I wanted him to come with me; but he shuffled out of it. I could see that he was quite afraid of you. Only fancy: he wanted me not to come. As if trembling I should be afraid of you, dearie. Vivie’s gravity deepens. But of course I told him it was all settled and comfortable between us, and that we were on the best of terms. She breaks down. Vivie: what’s the meaning of this? She produces a paper from an envelope; comes to the table; and hands it across. I got it from the bank this morning.
Vivie | It is my month’s allowance. They sent it to me as usual the other day. I simply sent it back to be placed to your credit, and asked them to send you the lodgment receipt. In future I shall support myself.
Mrs. Warren | Not daring to understand. Wasn’t it enough? Why didn’t you tell me? With a cunning gleam in her eye. I’ll double it: I was intending to double it. Only let me know how much you want.
Vivie | You know very well that that has nothing to do with it. From this time I go my own way in my own business and among my own friends. And you will go yours. She rises. Goodbye.
Mrs. Warren | Appalled. Goodbye?
Vivie | Yes: goodbye. Come: don’t let us make a useless scene: you understand perfectly well. Sir George Crofts has told me the whole business.
Mrs. Warren | Angrily. Silly old—She swallows an epithet, and then turns white at the narrowness of her escape from uttering it. He ought to have his tongue cut out. But I explained it all to you; and you said you didn’t mind.
Vivie | Steadfastly. Excuse me: I do mind. You explained how it came about. That does not alter it.
Mrs. Warren, silenced for a moment, looks forlornly at Vivie, who waits, secretly hoping that the combat is over. But the cunning expression comes back into Mrs. Warren’s face; and she bends across the table, sly and urgent, half whispering.
Mrs. Warren | Vivie: do you know how rich I am?
Vivie | I have no doubt you are very rich.
Mrs. Warren | But you don’t know all that that means: you’re too young. It means a new dress every day; it means theatres and balls every night; it means having the pick of all the gentlemen in Europe at your feet; it means a lovely house and plenty of servants; it means the choicest of eating and drinking; it means everything you like, everything you want, everything you can think of. And what are you here? A mere drudge, toiling and moiling early and late for your bare living and two cheap dresses a year. Think over it. Soothingly. You’re shocked, I know. I can enter into your feelings; and I think they do you credit; but trust me, nobody will blame you: you may take my word for that. I know what young girls are; and I know you’ll think better of it when you’ve turned it over in your mind.
Vivie | So that’s how it is done, is it? You must have said all that to many a woman, to have it so pat.
Mrs. Warren | Passionately. What harm am I asking you to do? Vivie turns away contemptuously. Mrs. Warren follows her desperately. Vivie: listen to me: you don’t understand: you’ve been taught wrong on purpose: you don’t know what the world is really like.
Vivie | Arrested. Taught wrong on purpose! What do you mean?
Mrs. Warren | I mean that you’re throwing away all your chances for nothing. You think that people are what they pretend to be—that the way you were taught at school and college to think right and proper is the way things really are. But it’s not: it’s all only a pretence, to keep the cowardly, slavish, common run of people quiet. Do you want to find that out, like other women, at forty, when you’ve thrown yourself away and lost your chances; or won’t you take it in good time now from your own mother, that loves you and swears to you that it’s truth—gospel truth? Urgently. Vivie: the big people, the clever people, the managing people, all know it. They do as I do, and think what I think. I know plenty of them. I know them to speak to, to introduce you to, to make friends of for you. I don’t mean anything wrong: that’s what you don’t understand: your head is full of ignorant ideas about me. What do the people that taught you know about life or about people like me? When did they ever meet me, or speak to me, or let anyone tell them about me?—the fools! Would they ever have done anything for you if I hadn’t paid them? Haven’t I told you that I want you to be respectable? Haven’t I brought you up to be respectable? And how can you keep it up without my money and my influence and Lizzie’s friends? Can’t you see that you’re cutting your own throat as well as breaking my heart in turning your back on me?
Vivie | I recognize the Crofts philosophy of life, mother. I heard it all from him that day at the Gardners’.
Mrs. Warren | You think I want to force that played-out old sot on you! I don’t, Vivie: on my oath I don’t.
Vivie | It would not matter if you did: you would not succeed. Mrs. Warren winces, deeply hurt by the implied indifference towards her affectionate intention. Vivie, neither understanding this nor concerning herself about it, goes on calmly. Mother: you don’t at all know the sort of person I am. I don’t object to Crofts more than to any other coarsely built man of his class. To tell you the truth, I rather admire him for being strong-minded enough to enjoy himself in his own way and make plenty of money instead of living the usual shooting, hunting, dining-out, tailoring, loafing life of his set merely because all the rest do it. And I’m perfectly aware that if I’d been in the same circumstances as my aunt Liz, I’d have done exactly what she did. I don’t think I’m more prejudiced or straitlaced than you: I think I’m less. I’m certain I’m less sentimental. I know very well that fashionable morality is all a pretence: and that if I took your money and devoted the rest of my life to spending it fashionably, I might be as worthless and vicious as the silliest woman could possibly be without having a word said to me about it. But I don’t want to be worthless. I shouldn’t enjoy trotting about the park to advertise my dressmaker and carriage builder, or being bored at the opera to show off a shopwindowful of diamonds.
Mrs. Warren | Bewildered. But—
Vivie | Wait a moment: I’ve not done. Tell me why you continue your business now that you are independent of it. Your sister, you told me, has left all that behind her. Why don’t you do the same?
Mrs. Warren | Oh, it’s all very easy for Liz: she likes good society, and has the air of being a lady. Imagine me in a cathedral town! Why, the very rooks in the trees would find me out even if I could stand the dullness of it. I must have work and excitement, or I should go melancholy mad. And what else is there for me to do? The life suits me: I’m fit for it and not for anything else. If I didn’t do it somebody else would; so I don’t do any real harm by it. And then it brings in money; and I like making money. No: it’s no use: I can’t give it up—not for anybody. But what need you know about it? I’ll never mention it. I’ll keep Crofts away. I’ll not trouble you much: you see I have to be constantly running about from one place to another. You’ll be quit of me altogether when I die.
Vivie | No: I am my mother’s daughter. I am like you: I must have work, and must make more money than I spend. But my work is not your work, and my way is not your way. We must part. It will not make much difference to us: instead of meeting one another for perhaps a few months in twenty years, we shall never meet: that’s all.
Mrs. Warren | Her voice stifled in tears. Vivie: I meant to have been more with you: I did indeed.
Vivie | It’s no use, mother: I am not to be changed by a few cheap tears and entreaties any more than you are, I daresay.
Mrs. Warren | Wildly. Oh, you call a mother’s tears cheap.
Vivie | They cost you nothing; and you ask me to give you the peace and quietness of my whole life in exchange for them. What use would my company be to you if you could get it? What have we two in common that could make either of us happy together?
Mrs. Warren | Lapsing recklessly into her dialect. We’re mother and daughter. I want my daughter. I’ve a right to you. Who is to care for me when I’m old? Plenty of girls have taken to me like daughters and cried at leaving me; but I let them all go because I had you to look forward to. I kept myself lonely for you. You’ve no right to turn on me now and refuse to do your duty as a daughter.
Vivie | Jarred and antagonized by the echo of the slums in her mother’s voice. My duty as a daughter! I thought we should come to that presently. Now once for all, mother, you want a daughter and Frank wants a wife. I don’t want a mother; and I don’t want a husband. I have spared neither Frank nor myself in sending him about his business. Do you think I will spare you?
Mrs. Warren | Violently. Oh, I know the sort you are—no mercy for yourself or anyone else. I know. My experience has done that for me anyhow: I can tell the pious, canting, hard, selfish woman when I meet her. Well, keep yourself to yourself: I don’t want you. But listen to this. Do you know what I would do with you if you were a baby again—aye, as sure as there’s a Heaven above us?
Vivie | Strangle me, perhaps.
Mrs. Warren | No: I’d bring you up to be a real daughter to me, and not what you are now, with your pride and your prejudices and the college education you stole from me—yes, stole: deny it if you can: what was it but stealing? I’d bring you up in my own house, so I would.
Vivie | Quietly. In one of your own houses.
Mrs. Warren | Screaming. Listen to her! listen to how she spits on her mother’s grey hairs! Oh! may you live to have your own daughter tear and trample on you as you have trampled on me. And you will: you will. No woman ever had luck with a mother’s curse on her.
Vivie | I wish you wouldn’t rant, mother. It only hardens me. Come: I suppose I am the only young woman you ever had in your power that you did good to. Don’t spoil it all now.
Mrs. Warren | Yes. Heaven forgive me, it’s true; and you are the only one that ever turned on me. Oh, the injustice of it, the injustice, the injustice! I always wanted to be a good woman. I tried honest work; and I was slave-driven until I cursed the day I ever heard of honest work. I was a good mother; and because I made my daughter a good woman she turns me out as if I were a leper. Oh, if I only had my life to live over again! I’d talk to that lying clergyman in the school. From this time forth, so help me Heaven in my last hour, I’ll do wrong and nothing but wrong. And I’ll prosper on it.
Vivie | Yes: it’s better to choose your line and go through with it. If I had been you, mother, I might have done as you did; but I should not have lived one life and believed in another. You are a conventional woman at heart. That is why I am bidding you goodbye now. I am right, am I not?
Mrs. Warren | Taken aback. Right to throw away all my money!
Vivie | No: right to get rid of you? I should be a fool not to? Isn’t that so?
Mrs. Warren | Sulkily. Oh, well, yes, if you come to that, I suppose you are. But Lord help the world if everybody took to doing the right thing! And now I’d better go than stay where I’m not wanted. She turns to the door.
Vivie | Kindly. Won’t you shake hands?
Mrs. Warren | After looking at her fiercely for a moment with a savage impulse to strike her. No, thank you. Goodbye.
Vivie | Matter-of-factly. Goodbye. Mrs. Warren goes out, slamming the door behind her. The strain on Vivie’s face relaxes; her grave expression breaks up into one of joyous content; her breath goes out in a half sob, half laugh of intense relief. She goes buoyantly to her place at the writing table; pushes the electric lamp out of the way; pulls over a great sheaf of papers; and is in the act of dipping her pen in the ink when she finds Frank’s note. She opens it unconcernedly and reads it quickly, giving a little laugh at some quaint turn of expression in it. And goodbye, Frank. She tears the note up and tosses the pieces into the wastepaper basket without a second thought. Then she goes at her work with a plunge, and soon becomes absorbed in her figures.